<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The scarlet gown or the history of all the present cardinals of Rome. Wherein is set forth the life, birth, interest, possibility, rich offices, dignities, and charges of every cardinal now living. Also their merits, vertures, and vices· Together with the cariage of the Pope and court of Rome. Written originally in Italian, and translated into English by H.C. Gent.</title>
            <title>Giusta statera de'porporati. English.</title>
            <author>N. N.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 203 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 89 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A89931</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing N53</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E1433_1</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R202993</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863105</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863105</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115287</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A89931)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115287)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 183:E1433[1])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The scarlet gown or the history of all the present cardinals of Rome. Wherein is set forth the life, birth, interest, possibility, rich offices, dignities, and charges of every cardinal now living. Also their merits, vertures, and vices· Together with the cariage of the Pope and court of Rome. Written originally in Italian, and translated into English by H.C. Gent.</title>
                  <title>Giusta statera de'porporati. English.</title>
                  <author>N. N.</author>
                  <author>Cogan, Henry.</author>
                  <author>Cross, Thomas, fl. 1632-1682, engraver.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[16], 162 [i.e. 164], [4] p., plate   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Humphrey Moseley, and are to be sold at his shop at the Prince's Armes in St Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Author's dedication signed: N.N.</note>
                  <note>A translation of: La giusta statera de'porporati.</note>
                  <note>Translator's dedication signed: Henry Cogan.</note>
                  <note>Title page in red and black.</note>
                  <note>The frontispiece is signed: T. Cross sculpsit.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: The just weight of the scarlet gowns.</note>
                  <note>P. 164 misnumbered 162.</note>
                  <note>With two final contents leaves.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "May. 24.".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cardinals --  Biography --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE SCARLET GOWN, Or the HISTORY Of all the preſent CARDINALS OF ROME.</p>
            <p>Wherein is ſet forth the LIFE, BIRTH, Intereſt, Poſſibility, rich Offices, Dignities, and charges of every Cardinal now living.</p>
            <p>Alſo their Merits, Vertues, and Vices; Together with the cariage of the POPE and Court of ROME.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written originally in Italian, and tranſlated into Engliſh by</hi> H. C. Gent.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Humphrey Moſeley,</hi> and are to be ſold at his ſhop at the <hi>Prince's Armes</hi> in <hi>St Pauls</hi> Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="frontispiece">
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:2"/>
            <p>
               <figure>
                  <figDesc>cardinal in habit</figDesc>
               </figure>
            </p>
            <p>A CARDINAL in his HABIT as hee sitts in the CONSISTORY.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>J. Croſs Sculpsit.</signed>
            </closer>
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
               <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
            </gap>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:3"/>
            <head>To the Right Honorable, and every way Noble Lord, <hi>John EARLE OF RVTLAND,</hi> Lord <hi>Roſſe</hi> of <hi>Hamlake, Trusbut</hi> and <hi>Belvoire.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>My LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His ſmall Treatiſe, which I have preſumed to recommend unto the world under your Honours Patronage, beſides the novel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie of the ſubject, ſo little, or not at all touched upon in any Booke, at leaſtwiſe that I have ſeen, ſpeaking our Tongue, cannot be but well received, as I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, by all ſuch as any way pretend to the knowledge of forraigne affaires, both for that it treates of ſo principall and
<pb facs="tcp:115287:4"/>active a body and ſociety of men, as that of the Colledge of Cadinalls, Princes Fellowes, as they are reputed, and the greate Councell, and Conſiſtory of that myſterious Head, the Pope of Rome; as alſo becauſe it diſcovers many par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularities of the practique as wel in the elections of the ſaid Cardinalls, as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe of their ſeverall intereſts, and hopes they may conceive to themſelves of arriving one day at Peters Chaire; and alſo what kind of Pope each of them is like to prove, in caſe he ſhould attaine to that honour. Moreover I make no queſtion but that it will be a very plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing thing to moſt men, to have ſuch a lively character by them, as my Author bere gives, of every one of thoſe Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politicians, and Councellors, who have ſuch an influence into all the debates and reſults of that pragmatique Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>intendent Court, and Conſiſtory: which
<pb facs="tcp:115287:4"/>Lords and Lawes it, or would wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly doe ſo, over the whole world. Of no leſſe ſatisfaction too, ſuppoſe I, it will bee to ſee ſo clearely chalked out all the ſeverall applications of all the Popiſh Princes and States, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the two great Kings of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spaine,</hi> by their Miniſters, ever Ledger about this Court, to the moſt po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litique, and powerfull of theſe Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals; out-vying each other in the offer of penſions, or indeavoring by the gift of ſpirituall dignities and preferments unto them, to inſure and ingage them as much as poſſible they may, to the eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pouſing the intereſts of that Crown, for which they ſerve; and yet what poore hold notwithſtanding, either of theſe Princes hath of them; and how apt they are upon very ſlight motives to range themſelves on the quite con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary faction, is a matter not unworthy
<pb facs="tcp:115287:5"/>of obſervation. Theſe and ſeverall o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Remarques touching the now Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinalls, the Pope at this day regnant, and his particular family, are preſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in this little Tract, which, I would willingly make my ſelfe beleeve, will bee as delightfull to the judicious, as it was pleaſing to mee in the tranſlating thereof. As for common and perfun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory Readers, I ſhall ſay as <hi>Antima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chus Clarius</hi> ſaid, when in the very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terim, as he was reciting a peece which hee had made, all but <hi>Plato</hi> left him, <hi>unus mihi Plato inſtar multo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum;</hi> for, ſo as your Honour be pleaſed to approve of, and favorablely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive it, the paines I have taken therein are abundantly ſatisfied, what reception ſoever it may finde of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; as having attained the maine end I propoſed to my ſelfe in the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of it; which was, that it might
<pb facs="tcp:115287:5"/>be as acceptable to your Lordſhip, as it is heartily deſired it ſhould bee, by him, who in all himble affection is,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>My Lord,</salute> 
               <signed>
                  <hi>Your Honours moſt devoted Servant</hi> Henry Cogan.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="histories">
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:6"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:115287:6"/>
            <head>THE JUST WEIGHT OF THE Scarlet Gowns.</head>
            <div n="1" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> Giovanni Carlo de Medici.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Prince <hi>Giovanni Carlo de Medici</hi> is Brother to the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> and Nephew to the Cardinal <hi>Carlo de Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d ci,</hi> at this day called the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of <hi>Toſcan.</hi> He was promoted by <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the tenth in the firſt Promotion, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his Holyneſs Nephew, at the inſtance of the great Duke, and the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal aforeſaid. He is a Prince of no mean Underſtanding, and an expert Souldier,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:115287:7"/>but more at Sea than on Land, becauſe he was for ſome time imployed in the charge of Generaliſſimo at Sea, commanding the Catholique Fleets; for which cauſe he alwaies hath been, and will be, moſt devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> beſides the open profeſſion all his Houſe makes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, which live under the protection of that Crown. He is a jovial Lord, and loves Women a little too much. He is by nature Covetous, nothing Bountifull, but rather Niggardly. All the Houſe of <hi>Medici</hi> is no great friend of the Family of the <hi>Barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini,</hi> for divers publique, and private cauſes, and in particular for the War made with thoſe Princes, to all the world known.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> Domenico Cecchini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DOmenico Cecchini,</hi> a Roman Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, about fifty three years of age: He hath been long a Prelate, and alwayes held good correſpondence with the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> who coming to be Pope promoted him joyntly, though he did not
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:115287:7"/>name him in the firſt Promotion; but he was the firſt named in the ſecond. Before he was Cardinal, his Holyneſs conferred upon him the charge of Datarie Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical; an Office verily of great profit, which he exerciſes ſtill now that he is Cardinal. He is a Learned man, and well verſt in the matters of the Court. It is ſaid, that this Cardinal was promoted by his Holyneſs, to gratifie him for ſome ſervices he had done him in divers occurrences, and particularly in the ſute depending be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the Marqueſs <hi>Giuſtiniano,</hi> and his Father; for that he had twice pronounced Sentence in favour of the Marqueſs, Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew to his Holyneſs; beſides ſeveral o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther cauſes, for which he merited the Popes grace. This perſonage is old, but not enough for the Papacy. He is a man Affable, Prudent, and repleat with Vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous qualities. In the time of his Prelate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip he was alwaies accounted Juſt, no notable defect being known in him. When he was young he took ſome recreation, but without ſcandal; howbeit now that he is Cardinal, he ſhews himſelf more laſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious, although he thinks his ſecrets &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligences are not penetrated into, whilſt he is very much pleaſed with women. He
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:115287:8"/>pretends enough unto the Papacy, is well looked upon in the Court, being loved, and reverenced of all, and maintains him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf neutral.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>III.</hi> Nicolò Albergati.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>NIcolò Albergati</hi> of the <hi>Bologneſe</hi> Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, forty years of age: He was Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Bologna,</hi> which dignity was re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned unto him in the beginning of the Papacy of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth by the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Colonna,</hi> being ſo charged with Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, that of the great Revenues of that Church the poor Lord could hardly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive two thouſand Crowns a year. The Prince <hi>Lodoviſio,</hi> who took to Wife the Popes Niepce, was deſirous to have a Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal in his Houſe for the new raiſing up the memory of his decayed Family; but becauſe he had no Brothers, nor other Kinſmen, he beſought his Holyneſs to grant him the grace to make the ſayd <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>colò Albergati,</hi> his Couſen by a Feminine line, Cardinal, and with a Brieve declare him Brother to his Excellency, upon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition that he ſhould call himſelf the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:115287:8"/>
                  <hi>Lodiviſio,</hi> as accordingly his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs vouchſafed to gratifie him. The ſaid Prince is ſince dead without Heirs, ſo that the <hi>Lodoviſian</hi> Family remains extinct. The Cardinal aforeſaid is very poor, and therefore is now relieved, and lodged, as the Prince's Brother, in his houſe. When as he was going to the reſidence of his Church, the Pope ordained him to paſs by <hi>Florence,</hi> with the title of Legat Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lical, and there in the name of his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to Chriſten a Son that was born to the great Duke; in which voyage he was by him ſumptuouſly entertained, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, at his departure from that City, he was by his Highneſs preſented with very fair, and rich Hangings of Tapeſtry; and his ſervants alſo with great gifts; but when his Eminencie would in ſome ſort have recompenced the ſame to his High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs Courtiers, they were expreſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den by him from taking of any thing. This Cardinal is of great underſtanding, rarely qualified, and of an holy conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, never omitting any Function which is to be performed by him in his Church; and being of an Exemplary life, he is much eſteeemed of by all the City. I am perſwaded, that he will continually
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115287:9"/>maintain himſelf in that conceit, which he hath at this preſent, that at length he may become Pope; and that happning, he would make the Church happy. He is affected to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> for that the Prince <hi>Lodoviſio</hi> was much inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſſed with that Majeſty, in regard all his Eſtate lay in the Kingdome of <hi>Naples.</hi> The <hi>French</hi> will much oppoſe him for di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers reſpects; the chief are, becauſe he is of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Faction; and that which is of greater conſequence, for that the ſaid <hi>French</hi> have deprived the Prince <hi>Lodovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſio</hi> his Brother, of the Principality of <hi>Pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ombino,</hi> which his Excellency bought of King <hi>Philip</hi> the fourth for the ſumme of five hundred thouſand Crowns; and now it is ſaid, that they will confer it on the Father of the Cardinal <hi>Mazarino.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115287:9"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>IV.</hi> Horatio Ginſtiniano.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>HOratio Giuſtiniano,</hi> ſeventy yeares of age, and Father of the Congregation of the Lord <hi>Philippo Neri:</hi> He is by birth a <hi>Genoueſe,</hi> and Couſen to the deceaſed Marqueſs, <hi>Giuſtiniano,</hi> whom he perſwaded to make the preſent Prince his heir, at ſuch time as he ſerved him in the place of his Chamberlain, though he were far from that Line, ſeeing the Prince is a native of <hi>Sicilia,</hi> and the deceaſed Marqueſs was a <hi>Genoueſe.</hi> In the beginning of the Papacy of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, it was held for an undoubted matter of every one, that the Prince would demand the Scarlet Gown, either for his Father, or his Brother; how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beit they were not onely not promoted, but by an Order, <hi>ore tenus,</hi> of his Holyneſs, they were baniſhed from <hi>Rome,</hi> with a De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration that they ſhould return into <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cilia,</hi> their country: And what was the occaſion of theſe motives could not be truly penetrated into; but for ſo much as I can underſtand, it was, becauſe the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the ſaid Prince having co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>menced a
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115287:10"/>ſute againſt his Son, upon pretence that he was to adminiſter the goods which the Marqueſs had left behind him, againſt the will of his Holyneſs, who, in the time when he was Cardinal, had with reitera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted inſtances prayed him to deſiſt from his pretenſion, but with much arrogance he went peeviſhly on in his obſtinate pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe. The Prince, as it is ſayd, out of his gratitude to his benefactors, demanded the Scarlet Gown for <hi>Giuſtiniano,</hi> who had beſides been an intimate friend of his Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lyneſs whilſt he was Cardinal. He is a man old in years, of good converſation, affable of acceſs, and of an exemplary life, but of mean underſtanding, and pretends not much to the Papacy; wherefore he declares not himſelf of any Faction, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maining independent and neutral. He ſeldom cuts his Beard, it may be for that he would ſeem older than he is. He is a poor Cardinal, having nothing elſe, than that his poor Patrimony, which he enjoyes in his Congregation, and what he comes to be ſupplyed with by his Holyneſs. He is Biſhop of <hi>Nocera</hi> in <hi>Umbria.</hi> He would not be any good Pope, either for the poor, or for the people, ſince, as a <hi>Genoueſe,</hi> he would encreaſe Taxes and Impoſitions. This
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115287:10"/>Cardinal is not much favoured in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred College; and although he ſhews himſelf neutral, yet is he inwardly much devoted to the Catholique King, but out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly is <hi>French.</hi> Our holy Father hath declared him grand Penitentiary.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>V.</hi> Cibò.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CIbò,</hi> thirty five years of age: He was a Prelate, and Sonne to the Prince of <hi>Maſſa</hi> &amp; <hi>Canara,</hi> and as ſoon as the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Pamphilio</hi> was made Pope, his Holyneſs declared him Steward of the Apoſtolical Palace; and becauſe the ſaid <hi>Cibò</hi> his Palace was near unto that of his Holynes, he made him a liberal tender thereof, to the end he might enlarge it with his, but the Pope re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed to accept of it as a gift, but took it by way of ſale; the rather, becauſe that Palace was ſubject to a ſtrict Feoffment in truſt. The ſaid <hi>Cibò</hi> held great correſpon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence of friendſhip and confidence with the aboveſaid <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> who knowing his merit, did in contemplation of <hi>Innocent</hi> the eighth, of the moſt noble Family of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115287:11"/>
                  <hi>Cibòes</hi> in <hi>Genoua,</hi> that was the original of the greatneſs of the <hi>Pamphilian.</hi> Houſe, by ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alting that Family unto Eccleſiaſtical dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and Prelatures, promote him the ſayd <hi>Cibò</hi> to the Scarlet Gown; and for that cauſe alſo took upon him the name of <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent</hi> the tenth. This young Cardinal is of much integrity, virtue, and goodneſs of life. He hath in all the time of his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lateſhip alwayes imitated the behaviour and carriage of the Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiring himſelf not onely from univerſal commerce, but alſo from that of Prelates, except it be in urgent occaſions. He is by nature Studious, and little given to Mirth, but is much delighted with hearing of Muſique. He is devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> for that his Progenitors lived un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of that Crown. He is loved, and well regarded, as well by the Pope, as by all the ſacred College. He pretends enough to the Papacy, for which end, it is believed, he lives ſo retired.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:115287:11"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Pier Luigi Caraffa.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PIer Luigi Caraffa</hi> was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth made Biſhop of <hi>Tricario</hi> in <hi>Rego;</hi> and afterwards by the ſame Pope ſent Nuntio into <hi>Germany,</hi> and to <hi>Liege</hi> in <hi>Elan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders;</hi> at which time <hi>Sachetti,</hi> the Biſhop of <hi>Gravina,</hi> was by him alſo ſent into <hi>Spain,</hi> with a purpoſe to promote both of them to the Scarlet Gown; but at the inſtance of the <hi>Colonneſi, Caraffa</hi> remained exclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, <hi>Sachetti</hi> being onely promoted: And after he had abode a long time in that his employment of Nuntio he was recalled to the Court, where the poor Lord thought to receive the due reward of his labours; And being arrived at <hi>Rome,</hi> after his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuance there ſome weeks, he reſolved cunningly to try his fortune, by craving leave, as he did, to go unto his Reſidence, to the end that by the anſwer the Pope ſhould give him, he might conjecture what his good, or bad diſpoſition was towards him, and ſo might afterwards direct his life accordingly: But <hi>Urban,</hi> not onely gave him his benediction with both hands, but<gap reason="illegible: missing" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:115287:12"/>ſayd unto him, <hi>My Lord, goe the more cheer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully, becauſe we will not forget your deſerts;</hi> Which <hi>Caraffa</hi> hearing, abſented himſelf from the Court, and arriving at his Reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he never went from it, untill his Holyneſs, after ſome ten or eleven years paſt of his Papacy, cauſed him to be called to the Court in the year 1642. ſo as all the world was perſwaded, that it was to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote him unto the Scarlet Gown; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing arrived there, it was publiſhed, that he was come to viſit the Temple of the Apoſtles; and not called by his Holyneſs; and the occaſion thereof was, becauſe the <hi>Colonneſi,</hi> foreſeeing that the Scarlet Gown was deſigned for him, upon his arrival, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned anew to preſs the Pope, that he ſhould not promote him; and among the reſt <hi>Donna Anna Barbarina,</hi> Wife to <hi>Don Tadeo,</hi> went unto him, and with reiterated prayers, and much weeping, perſwaded <hi>Urban</hi> not to make him Cardinal, as indeed he did not. But <hi>Urban</hi> himſelf repented him of it, for he was heard one day to ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter theſe preciſe words, <hi>God forgive him, who was the cauſe, that I did not make</hi> Pier Luigi Caraffa <hi>Cardinal;</hi> and this he ſayd many times, according to report: howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he was fain to goe away from <hi>Rome,</hi>
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:115287:12"/>as he came: but <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, when as in the ſecond Promotion he promoted his Nephew, gave him the Scarlet Gown, becauſe he knew him worthy of that dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and <hi>Caraffa</hi> himſelf expected it from his hands, as ſoon as he heard of his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs aſſumption to the Papacy; for he well remembred theſe words which he ſpake to him, when as in the time of <hi>Urban</hi> he was departing towards the Reſidence of his Church; <hi>My Lord, it grieves me much, that your Lordſhip goes from Court with ſo little ſatisfaction, not having received the deſerved reward of your labours.</hi> Unto whom <hi>Caraffa</hi> anſwered, <hi>I will pray our Lord God, that he will make me worthy to receive it from your hands;</hi> to this <hi>Pamphilio</hi> replyed, <hi>I have no ſuch pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion, but be aſſured if it ſhould happen to be ſo, you ſhall be one of the firſt I will think upon;</hi> as indeed it fell out; for after the promotion of his Nephew, he was the next that he gave the Hat unto, being at that time in his biſhoprick of <hi>Tricaria:</hi> and beſides his Merits, there was a certain obligation of kindred between them; for whilſt <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> was a Prelate, and Nuntio at <hi>Naples,</hi> having brought along with him thither all his Family, together with his brother and his wife, his Nephew, called <hi>Camillo Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>philio,</hi>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:115287:13"/>the now Husband of the Princeſs <hi>Roſſano,</hi> was born in the ſayd city of <hi>Naples,</hi> and the Prince <hi>Don Tiberio Caraffa,</hi> this Cardinals brother, was his Godfather. This perſon is moſt deſerving, both for his own good qualities, and the ſervices he hath done to the Apoſtolick Sea. He is exceeding well verſt in all matters of the Conſiſtories and Congregations; his Votes are held in great eſteem, and the Pope makes much account of him; ſo doth the ſacred College, and every one elſe. He is a man of approved goodneſs of life, and hath alwayes ſhunned converſations for the avoyding of ſcandals; he ſeeks, as much as may be, to live retired, devout<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly reverencing God, and making all his Family to doe the like; and it is held for certain, by them which know him, that he is ſtill a Virgin. This Cardinal hath in the ſacred College no Enemies, either ſecret or open, unleſs it be the <hi>Colonneſi,</hi> who, as before, would not have had him Cardinal, ſo doe they not now for certain deſire he ſhould riſe to the Papacy, but will uſe all their force and power to keep him from it. He would be a good Pope, for the benefit, not onely of the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Church, but of all Chriſtendome. He
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115287:13"/>hath many, and divers Nephews, but the moſt beloved, and neareſt to him, are the Sonnes of the Count <hi>Celano,</hi> of the Houſe of <hi>Piccolomini;</hi> and thoſe of the Marqueſs of <hi>Anſé:</hi> Howbeit if ever he ſhould come to be Pope, <hi>Teatino</hi> would be the reigning Cardinal, unto whom he hath reſigned the Biſhoprick of <hi>Tricario;</hi> a man Learned, of good Life, and great Authority. The Prince of <hi>Biſignano, Don Tiberio Caraffa,</hi> his Brother, is Knight of the Golden-Fleece. He is curteous, affable, of an exemplary life, and very charitable, ſo that for his noble qualities he is well looked upon, and univerſally beloved of all the City of <hi>Naples,</hi> which calls him <hi>Pater Patriae,</hi> for that he favours the poor ſo much.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>VII.</hi> Federico Sforza.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FEderico Sforza,</hi> four and forty years of age, a <hi>Roman</hi> Nobleman, and Brother to the Duke of that Surname. He was a Prelate in the College of the participa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting Protonotaries in the time of <hi>Urban,</hi> and had no other imployment than to be
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:115287:14"/>Vice-Legat in <hi>Avignon,</hi> being ſent thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by the Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> the Legat, with an intent to promote him alſo to the Cardinalſhip, but it did not follow for ſome private intereſts. <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, for that he would not ſee a Houſe ſo renowned, and ſo well affected unto him, to be without the Scarlet Gown, made him Cardinal. He is a man of good under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, but not very rich, and therefore ſomewhat miſerable. His Holyneſs after the flight of the Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> made him Vicechamberlain of the holy Church. He is a jovial Lord, loves Comedies and Feaſts; and in particular when he was a Prelate, he delighted much in company. His Inclination is <hi>French</hi> for two reaſons; the firſt, becauſe he was Vice-Legat at <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vignon;</hi> and the ſecond, for that there is continually ſeen in his Palace great ſtore of <hi>French;</hi> but he ſeems to be neutral, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be for the Pope: Others ſay, that he will become <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> in regard of the feudes, and eſtates, which Duke <hi>Sfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>za,</hi> his brother, poſſeſſeth in the State of <hi>Milan;</hi> being lately too left heir of many Gaſtles by the death of a <hi>Milaneſe</hi> Lord, his Kinſman. He is no great friend of Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> becauſe he cauſed
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115287:14"/>him, upon hope of making him Cardinal; to ſell him at a very low rate the Palace of <hi>Sforza's</hi> Court, ſince called Cardinal <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonio</hi>'s; but being afterwards given by the ſaid <hi>Antonio</hi> to the Queen of <hi>France,</hi> it is now named the Royal Palace, where the Ambaſſador of the moſt Chriſtian King reſides; and where alſo the Princes and Lords that come out of <hi>France</hi> doe uſually lodge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>VIII.</hi> Tiberio Cenci.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>TIberio Cenci,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> fifty five years old; he was a Biſhop, and promoted to the Scarlet Gown at the inſtance of the Prince <hi>Borgheſe,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, as the neareſt of his Kinſmen that was ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable of that dignity, for that there was none other of the houſe of <hi>Borgheſe</hi> which was fit, and of age to receive the Hat. He was poor, and therefore was aſſiſted with a good ſum of money by the ſayd Prince, who offered him for his habitation the lodgings of the Cardinal <hi>Borgheſe</hi> in his own Palace; but he was thanked by <hi>Cenci,</hi>
                  <pb n="18" facs="tcp:115287:15"/>without accepting thereof, ſaying, <hi>that he would make uſe of his favour upon occaſion;</hi> nevertheleſs the ſaid Prince beſtowed on him ſeveral ſuits of Tapeſtry hangings, and furnitures for chambers. The ſayd <hi>Cenci</hi> is Nephew to Cardinal <hi>Lanti,</hi> in whoſe houſe he remained ſome time after he had reeeived the Scarlet Gown, but now he is removed into the houſe where Cardinal <hi>Pio</hi> dwelt, in the <hi>Ceſarinies</hi> ſtreet. He is a perſon capable of being Pope, of ſome value, and well looked upon by the Court, but he is of no credit with the Princes, though he be a good man, as ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been a long time exerciſed in the Congregation of the Lord <hi>Philippo Neri</hi> in the new Church. He hath no defect in him, and if he ſhould live to a Conclave, he might likewiſe pretend to the Papacy, and the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan</hi> would ayd him much, in regard he is the Kinſman of his Kinſmen; but I am perſwaded, that whoſoever ſhall goe about to raiſe him, will labour in vain, for that the memory is yet freſh of that cruell and infamous ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſs happening unto the Houſe of the <hi>Cenci,</hi> which I will not leave unrecounted. There were three children of the ſayd Houſe, one Daughter and two Sons, moſt
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115287:15"/>noble <hi>Romans:</hi> whoſe Father being very rich, and well ſtricken in years, was ſo wretchedly covetous that he would allow his Sons in a manner nothing, nor marry his Daughter; who for her beauty was much deſired, &amp; ſued unto by the beſt No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility of <hi>Rome,</hi> becauſe he would not part with money. This old man too was ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what crackt brain'd, ſo that he would oftentimes play many odde pranks; in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard whereof the Daughter one day call<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing her Nurſe, ſayd unto her, that they ſhould doe well to take her Father, and throw him out of the window, for ſo he being dead they ſhould be maſters of all. The Nurſe, together with one of the Sons, gave conſent to her motion, and having accordingly put it in execution, they fell a weeping &amp; crying out as ſoon as the deed was done, that the old man in one of his frantick fits had caſt himſelf out of the window. This comming to the ears of the Magiſtrates, they were all three, together with the younger Son, committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon; and diligent inquiſition being made on the body of the deceaſed, to ſee whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther by force he had been thrown out by others, or that he had precipitated him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, there were ſignes found ſufficient to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115287:16"/>put the delinquents to torture. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon being examined, and comming to be rack'd, the young mayd, that was ſome ſixteen years of age, ſuddenly confeſſed ever thing, which being acknowledged by the other two, they were condemned to death; and afterwards being brought to to the place of execution, the Maid and her Brother were both beheaded; and the other brother, that was in a manner but a child, and not reputed any way guilty, was onely made to ſtand under the Scaf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold all the while. Now in regard of all this, I ſhould think it a ſtrange matter that ever this Cardinal ſhould attain to the Papacy: howſoever he is a man affable, courteous in his dealings, and of a good diſpoſition. He hath not declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf of any party, but profeſſeth to be neutral.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:115287:16"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>VI.</hi> Benedetto Odeſchalco.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BEnedetto Odeſchalco,</hi> a Nobleman of the City of <hi>Milan,</hi> 45 years of age; he was a rich Prelate, and a long time courted <hi>Barbarino,</hi> out of a deſire he had to be Clerk of the Chamber; which <hi>Don Barbarino</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed unto him, having to that effect re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived the money for it before hand; yet for all that he could never obtain his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent. But after the death of <hi>Urban,</hi> he fell to courting the Lady <hi>Olimpia,</hi> Siſter-in-law to his Holyneſs, who reigneth at this pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent; and having divers times preſented her with gifts, he at length got into her favour, and in particular by an action uſed by him, which is worthy to be noted; and it was this. Going one day, about the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the Aſſumption of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, to the houſe of the ſaid Lady <hi>Olim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>via,</hi> a Goldſmith came and ſhewed her a Cupbord of very fair Plate to ſell; which ſhe having viewed very well, in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſaid <hi>Odeſchalco,</hi> and other Lords, ſhe ſaid, that it was a curious and goodly Cupbord of Plate, but that ſhe was
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115287:17"/>a poor Widdow, and was not able to buy it; and ſaying ſo, paſt into her chamber. Whereupon <hi>Odeſchalco</hi> calling the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith unto him, asked him what the price of it was; and being agreed, he paid him down eight thouſand Crowns for it; then, without ſaying any thing elſe, he ſent it in as a preſent from him to the ſaid Lady <hi>O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>limpia:</hi> who ſeeing ſo noble a gift, was ſo taken with it, that ſhe went to the Pope, and begged of him for <hi>Odeſchalco</hi> not only the Clerkſhip of the Chamber, but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards alſo the Scarlet Gown. This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal is of mean underſtanding, and though he hath ſpent much, yet he is rich, ſplendid, affable in his ſpeech, and well affected to all the <hi>Pamphilian</hi> Houſe. Whilſt he was a Prelate he was much given to Sports, Comedies, and Feaſts; now he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtains both from common commerce, and converſation. He is a vaſſal to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique King, and therefore will be alwaies of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Faction, unleſs it bee when his Country ſhall change its Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth hath in theſe Promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions created eleven Cardinals, and two Hats remained vacant; but by the death of the Cardinal <hi>Borgia</hi> in <hi>Spain,</hi> of the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:115287:17"/>Cardinal <hi>Capucino</hi> in <hi>Rome,</hi> and alſo of the Cardinal <hi>Farneſe,</hi> there comes to be five Hats vacant in the ſacred Colledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>X.</hi> Fabritio Savelli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAbritio Savelli,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> and the ſon of Prince <hi>Savelli,</hi> Ambaſſacor in this Court for the Emperors Majeſty. He is old in years, having ſerved in the Wars of <hi>Germany</hi> with the title of General: He hath been oftentimes made a priſoner by the <hi>Switzers,</hi> and the laſt time that he was ſo, he corrupted his guard, and fled toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with them to <hi>Rome;</hi> where rewarding them, he gave them a houſe and means to live withall. In the time of the War that <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth waged againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> he was declared General of the Army that oppoſed the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> wherein he carryed himſelf ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what ſlackly, for that he might have dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nified the enemy, and did it not; the rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of it was, becauſe he conſidered the decrepit age of <hi>Urban,</hi> and the little time that he was likely to live; ſo that he held
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:115287:18"/>it no wiſdom to make ſo potent a Prince, as he was, his enemy; wherefore he was called home from the Camp, and <hi>Don Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eo Barbarino,</hi> his Holyneſs Nephew, was ſent thither as Generaliſſimo. This Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, both for the Antiquity and Nobility of it, enjoyes divers prerogatives and priviledges; amongſt the which one is, that in the time of the vacancy of the Apoſto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Sea, he keeps the Keyes of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave, and may for the guard of his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon raiſe ſouldiers at the charge of the Chamber, ſo far forth as need ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire: And he may alſo execute Juſtice on the lives, not only of private men, but likewiſe of thoſe of quality; and in that of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, he committed to pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon certain Regiſters, that by ſecret waies carried Letters into the Conclave to ſome Cardinals; and, it is ſaid, that he ſent them afterwards into the Galleys, having alſo threatned to hang them: <hi>Signior Giulca Donati,</hi> Auditor to Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> was beheaded in the Caſtle of St. <hi>Angelo,</hi> for going about without leave to ſpeak with the ſaid Cardinal his Maſter; and to that effect are Gallows erected in St. <hi>Peters</hi> Piatza. This Family hath had two Popes, and a great many Cardinals; and it was
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115287:18"/>verily beleeved, a little before <hi>Urban</hi> the eighths death, that the deceaſed Cardinal <hi>Savelli</hi> would have been Pope, becauſe he was a man of an approved good life, cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritable, and indued with all the qualities appertaining to an high Biſhop; and it was the rather ſo beleeved, for that in cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain mountainous places, as one goes to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the Sea-ſhore of <hi>Siena,</hi> there was a Marble ſtone found with an Epitaph upon it, which ſaid, that in the year 1645. there ſhould be a Pope of the houſe of <hi>Savelli,</hi> and in the very ſame ſtone were the armes of <hi>Savelli</hi> engraven. This <hi>Fabritio,</hi> whilſt his Uncle the Cardinal lived, was called the Abbot <hi>Savelli;</hi> but his ſaid Uncle be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Arch-biſhop of <hi>Salerno,</hi> obtained leave to reſign his Arch-biſhoprick, to the end it might be conferred on his ſaid Nephew <hi>Fabritio,</hi> as accordingly it was; and going afterwards to his Reſidence there, he car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried himſelf in ſuch ſort, as he was well regarded by the people of that place: In proceſs of time he began to grow ſo cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous, and deſirous of gain, that he would not have ſtuck to have made away half a ſcore men for money. It is not many moneths ſince he returned to the Court, where he abode till ſuch time as he was
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115287:19"/>promoted; for <hi>Innocent</hi> being as ardent in raiſing the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobility, as <hi>Urban</hi> was intent in depreſſing it, he held it inconve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient, that ſo renowned a Houſe ſhould remain deprived of thoſe honors, with which in times paſt they alwaies ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abounded; wherefore his Holyneſs made this <hi>Fabritio</hi> a Cardinal; who is a man of good converſation, amiable, gratefull, and very underſtanding; but with all he is proud, making little account of other Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies. Theſe <hi>Savelli</hi> are altogether <hi>Auſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an,</hi> and are of near of kin to the Cardinal <hi>Montalto,</hi> whoſe heirs they ſhall be after his deceaſe; they are alſo allyed to the <hi>Orſini</hi> and <hi>Ceſarini.</hi> This Cardinal is no great friend to the Ambaſſador of <hi>France,</hi> who affronted him by denying him audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, becauſe he went firſt to viſit the Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſador of <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:115287:19"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XI.</hi> Franceſco Cherubino.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Cherubino da monte Bodio nella Marca;</hi> this man came privately to <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſerved the Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> at this preſent Pope; a long time, with great ſatisfaction to his Holyneſs: after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards finding himſelf able for it, he put himſelf into the Prelacie, and having ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſed divers charges in the Eccleſiaſtical ſtate, it fortuned that <hi>Don Pamphilio</hi> was made Pope, who out of gratitude to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward him, received him anew into his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice in the Apoſtolical Palace, and decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red him his ſecret Auditor: After ſome time of reſidence in the Apoſtolical Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, he was promoted to the dignity of Cardinal, with five others. This perſon is a man of ripe years, prudent, and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; divers will have him to be ſomewhat a kin to his Holyneſs. He hath great Penſions, is of a good diſpoſition, and a friend to the poor: He is not much for the Princes, becauſe he is a private man, but if he live, his Holyneſs, no doubt will confer on him ſome Apoſtolical, or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vincial
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:115287:20"/>Legateſhip, to the end he may give a proof of his abilities.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XII.</hi> Chriſtoffero Vidman.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CHriſtoffero Vidman,</hi> a native of the City of <hi>Venice;</hi> ſome will have him deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of baſe parentage; and the truth is, his Anceſtors were but mean perſons, that in <hi>Venice</hi> made profeſſion of Merchants Factors, who in proceſs of time attaining to ſome wealth, began to trade in Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſe themſelves; whereby <hi>Giovanni Vidman,</hi> the Father of the now reigning Sons, got no ordinary riches, in ſuch ſort as he bought divers Caſtles and Lands in <hi>Carinthia</hi> and <hi>Ortenburg:</hi> His Sons were in number five, that is, <hi>Giovanni Paolo,</hi> which is dead, <hi>Lodovico, Martin, David,</hi> and <hi>Chriſtofforo,</hi> the preſent Cardinal; who to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with his brother <hi>David</hi> came to <hi>Rome</hi> in the time of <hi>Urban,</hi> where <hi>Chriſtoffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ro,</hi> putting himſelf into the Prelacy, bought the Clerk of the Chambers place, and ſo began to make ſhew of the Talent
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:115287:20"/>which God had given him. Afterwards the Auditor of the ſame Chambers place being voyd, by <hi>Urbans</hi> promoting him that enjoyed it to the Scarlet Gown, the ſaid <hi>Chriſtofforo</hi> received that charge alſo, upon paying the uſual price for it. But within a while <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth dyed, and <hi>Pamphilio, Innocent</hi> the tenth, was created Pope: who ſeeing the want the Chamber was in, ſupplyed it after the wonted man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, by ſelling the Offices of the Clerk and Auditor of the Apoſtolical Chamber, which <hi>Vidman</hi> poſſeſſed, who was there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore promoted to the Scarlet Gown, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Lord <hi>Raggi,</hi> Treaſurer Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the holy Church, and four other perſons, the ſeventh of <hi>October</hi> in the year 1647. This Cardinal is of a goodly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence, of a luſty complexion, young, and one that loves the world. His Brother <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> is of the ſame condition he is of, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighting in Sports, Comedies, and Feaſts, and that not without Women. They are now Gentlemen of <hi>Venice,</hi> to which Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litie they attained by paying down an hundred thouſand Duckats for it, accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Decree made by that Repub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique in the time of their neceſſities, oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſioned by their War againſt the <hi>Turk.</hi>
                  <pb n="30" facs="tcp:115287:21"/>This Cardinal is of a good diſpoſition, merry, facetious, amiable, friendly, and courteous, reſpecting every one, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouring them that honour him; he is alſo very ſplendid, ſo that he may well be ſaid to be derived of the noble <hi>German</hi> and <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>netian</hi> Nation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XIII.</hi> Lorenzo Raggi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LOrenzo Raggi,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Genoua</hi> of the new Nobility, Nephew to the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaſed Cardinal of the ſame ſurname; which deceaſed Cardinal putting himſelf into the Prelacie in the time of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, bought the place of Clerk of the Chamber, as alſo that afterwards of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditor of the ſame: And becauſe he was not onely ſimple, but altogether ignorant, he was every where known to be ſuch; for he never imployed himſelf in any other thing but in giving publique audience <hi>pro forma:</hi> His ignorance was openly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covered in all occaſions, and in particular in a ſute depending before him, where the Proctor of the one ſide, deſiring to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:115287:21"/>his Clients cauſe, found that the Auditor <hi>Raggi</hi> adhered to the adverſe party, and therefore began to demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate unto his honourable Lordſhip many lively reaſons for the maintainance there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, alledging divers Authors, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular ſaid, that the <hi>Codice</hi> in ſuch a Law made good his Plea. My Lord <hi>Raggi,</hi> in regard that which the Proctor affirmed was prejudicial to the party he favoured, conceived according to his ignorant opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, that the <hi>Codice</hi> was ſome witneſs to be produced in judgement, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſaid unto the Proctor theſe preciſe words, <hi>I will throughly chaſtiſe this Codice;</hi> and then demanded of him where he was, becauſe he would have him apprehended and ſent to the Gallyes. The Proctor an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered that he was to be found in his Cli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents Advocates houſe; whereupon he commanded a Notary to ſend ſome Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers along with the Proctor to the ſaid Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocates houſe, to apprehend the <hi>Codice;</hi> which being accordingly performed, the <hi>Codice</hi> was delivered unto them, who thought it was ſome prohibited book, and that therefore they were ordered to ſeize upon it; ſo they carried it to my Lord <hi>Raggi,</hi> who was then Auditor of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber;
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:115287:22"/>and the Proctor being arrived there with them, opened the book, and found out the Law by him before cited; which <hi>Raggi</hi> ſeeing, remained like a ſtatue, quite beſides himſelf. Now the ſport and paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time that was made of this matter throughout the City came to the eares of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, who was ready to burſt with laughing at it. Another time it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that another Proctor came before him to defend another cauſe at his houſe, which was juſt oppoſite to the <hi>Capranick</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lege, where were divers mad wags, who as often as they ſaw him look out of his window, cryed out, <hi>Bragone, bragone,</hi> that is, great breeches or ſlops; ſo that after he was made Cardinal, the common people ever after called him, as they had done, <hi>Bragone.</hi> Now whilſt the Proctor was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive in pleading of his cauſe, he an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered the Scholars of the ſaid Colledge, ſaying, <hi>the Galleys, the Galleys.</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor beleeving that he ſpake in that man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner againſt his Client, anſwered, <hi>My hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Lord, the poor man, my Client, deſerves not the puniſhment of the Galleys;</hi> but in the mean time <hi>Raggi,</hi> ſeeing thoſe too inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Scholars continue on ſtill mocking him, cryed out with a loud voice, <hi>Not the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:115287:22"/>Galleys, but the Gallows;</hi> which the Proctor hearing, ſaid, as it were vext, <hi>My Lord, ſince you will needs ſend to the Galleys, and hang one that no waies deſerves it, you may doe as you pleaſe;</hi> and ſo went away from him. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he was made Cardinal, he cauſed a Cardinals garments to be made for him, and putting them on, he walked up and down his houſe, and asked of his friends how they became him, and whether he did not walk gravely enough in them: And out of the great deſire he had to be a Cardinal, he went one day to the Pope, who loved him for his harmleſs ſimplicity, and after he had kiſſed his foot, he ſaid, <hi>Holy Father, make me a Cardinal, and ſo give ſatisfaction to the poor old man my Father.</hi> After he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown, he went to thank his Holyneſs, and imbra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing him ſaid, I cannot chuſe but hugge and kiſs you, for joy that you have made me a Cardinal. Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lighted ſo much in this man, as can hardly be expreſt, the truth whereof doth appear by the effects; for he not onely made him a Cardinal, but alſo at his inſtance gave the Treaſurorſhip General to <hi>Lorenzo Rag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi,</hi> his Nephew; unto whom, for a cloſing up of all other his extravagancies, he ſaid
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:115287:23"/>openly; Nephew, if you will arrive unto that which I have attained unto, you muſt labour to carry your ſelf, and do as I have done. Whereat, not onely all the ſtanders by, but even his Nephew himſelf, could not forbear laughing. Not long after the Treaſurorſhip was conferred on <hi>Lorenzo,</hi> the Cardinal his Uncle died, and made his Brother, the Marqueſſe <hi>Raggi,</hi> his heir; for which cauſe there hath been a good while ſome diſtaſt between the two brothers, the Treaſuror and the Marqueſs. The ſaid <hi>Lorenzo Raggi</hi> was in the time of <hi>Urban</hi> Superintendant of the Impoſitions laid upon the State Eccleſiaſtical; during which charge of his, there fell out many diſorders; for in the <hi>Barbarini</hi> War, the Souldiers could not have their pay; ſo that two dayes after <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth was aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumed to the Papacy, thoſe Souldiers that were appointed for the guard of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave began to mutinie, becauſe his Holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs having ordained that every one of them ſhould have four moneths pay, and ſo be diſmiſſed, <hi>Raggi</hi> would give them but two; wherewith they being very much incenſed, fell furiouſly to aſſaulting the houſe he was in, which they ſacked, and plundered all the money they found in it;
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:115287:23"/>chaſing the ſaid <hi>Raggi</hi> into <hi>Don Tadeos</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace, where he ſhut up himſelf for fear of his life; but the ſouldiers beſieged him in it, and were bringing two peeces of Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>non to beat down the gates, had not <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the tenth, newly elected, with his pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence given remedy thereunto. Howſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his Holyneſs was much offended with him for this buſineſs, and every body thought, that he would have deprived him of his charge, and made him reſign up his Treaſurors place; but after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, at the interceſſion of divers per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, the matter went no further, and in the end he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown in the ſecret conſiſtory of the fourth of <hi>October</hi> 1647. This Cardinal is young, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout ſome five and twenty years of age, and of a good converſation, but ambitious, and covetous: He is not over-learned, nor ignorant, but holds the mean betwixt both.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:115287:24"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIV.</hi> Franceſco Maidalchini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Maidalchini,</hi> a native of the City of <hi>Viterbo,</hi> and Nephew by her Brother to the Lady <hi>Olimpia,</hi> the Siſter-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>law of Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth. This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal was a youth void of all manner of converſation, not being able to carry him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with any civility; and therefore he was kept in a Colledge, to learn not onely humane letters, but alſo good manners. Suddenly, upon the making of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth Pope, the Lady <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> his Aunt, procured an Abbots place for him; with which he lived reaſonably well, but altogether unknown to the world. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, the Lord <hi>Camillo Pamphilio,</hi> Sonne to the ſame Lady <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> and the Popes onely Nephew, being promoted to the Scarlet Gown, it hapned, that by the death of the Prince <hi>Don Paolo Borgheſe,</hi> the Lady <hi>Donna Olimpia Aldobrandina,</hi> Princeſs of <hi>Roſſana,</hi> his Wife, became a Widdow, with whoſe beauty and riches the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Pamphilio</hi> was ſo taken, as he abandon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Scarlet Gown, and married her.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:115287:24"/>But the poor Prince <hi>Don Camillo</hi> was much troubled thereupon, for that by the Papal Buls it was ordered, that the Cardinals which renounced their Hats, and took Wives, ſhould not enter into the <hi>Roman</hi> Court for a certain prefixed time of ſome moneths: Howbeit he obeyed, in hope he ſhould obtain of the Pope his Uncle a diſpenſation for his return unto the Court. But <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> his Mother, conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that if he and his Wife ſhould come to abide in the Court, the authority and power which ſhe had with the Pope might be diſturbed, laboured with all her indea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to keep the Pope from permitting their return thither; ſaying, that it was not fit to have ſo many <hi>Olimpian</hi> Ladies in the Court, becauſe one alone (meaning her ſelf) was enough. This comming to the eares of the Princeſs, <hi>Don Camillo</hi>'s Wife, ſhe, as a Lady extracted of ſo illuſtrious an Houſe, could not chuſe but very much re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent it, inſomuch as ſhe imparted it to many Cardinals of the Court; and the like did alſo the Prince <hi>Don Camillo</hi> her Huſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>band, with threatning revenge. Which being underſtood by the widdow Mother, <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> who being of a man-like, bitter, and vindicative nature, was ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voked
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:115287:25"/>therewith, that hearing how his Holyneſs was minded to promote to the Scarlet Gown one of the Houſe of <hi>Pamphi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lio,</hi> ſhe went and ſo conjured him, as ſhe diverted him from that purpoſe, and with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all drew him to promiſe to make the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid <hi>Franceſco Maidalchini</hi> Cardinal, as accordingly he did in the Conſiſtory of the ſeventh of <hi>October</hi> 1647. At which pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion, not onely the Court ſtood ama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, but all the forraign Princes likewiſe, who mightily blamed it: But it was brought to paſs by the cunning of <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> to the end ſhe might introduce him into the ſame command of the State Eccleſiaſtical, which <hi>Barbarino</hi> had enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed under <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the eighth; and having given a beginning unto it, in regard he was unfit for buſineſs, ſhe, with the conſent of his Holyneſs, put him under the ſchooling of the Cardinals <hi>Panzirolo</hi> and <hi>Cherubino,</hi> that he might be inſtructed by them in the affairs of the Court; and not contented herewith, ſhe oftentimes ſolicited the Pope, becauſe he had no Cardinal Nephew, to declare him for ſuch, to no other end but to take away all hope from the Prince, her Son, and his Wife, of future authority and adherence, &amp; his Holyneſs was enclined to
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:115287:25"/>condiſcend thereunto. But it comming to the ears of the Nuns his Siſters, they all joyned together, with the Princeſs <hi>Lodovi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia,</hi> the Prince <hi>Camillo</hi>'s Siſter, and going in great fury to the Pope, they with much reſentment gave him to underſtand, that it was very inconvenient for him to declare any perſon of a ſtrange Family Cardinal Nephew; and that yeelding thereunto, he would give all the world occaſion to talk of it: and in this manner they drew his Holyneſs to promiſe them, that he would never permit any ſuch thing. About the ſame time the Pope fell ſick of a retention of urine, ſo that it was thought he would have dyed: whereupon the Prince <hi>Camillo</hi> went in ſecret to viſit his Uncle, who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived him very lovingly, and calling Cardinal <hi>Panziroli</hi> to him, he willed him to deliver unto the ſaid Prince his Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phew the money that was in his keeping, which amounted unto two millions and an half; and then to keep the Mother from beng diſtaſted at his coming to the Court, he cauſed it to be given out, that he was gone to <hi>Caprarola,</hi> whilſt in the mean time he lay cloſe in a private houſe unknown. But <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> underſtanding that the money was conſigned unto the Prince her
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:115287:26"/>Son, took on ſo exceedingly at it, that ſhe remained ſome daies ſick therwith; for ſhe verily beleeved that it ſhould have come unto her hands, according to the hope his Holyneſs had given her of it; and they continue ſtill with great diſturbance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt themſelves, in the tearms whereof I have before given ſome hint. It is held for certain, that our Lord the Pope very much repented the promoting of <hi>Maidal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chini,</hi> in regard it is univerſally known how ignorant he is, being ſcarce able to talk; and therefore he is of ſo little eſteem with the other Cardinals, that they make, as it were, a gaming ſtock of him. Beſides, he himſelf never humours any one, nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turns a curteſie to any that honours him; and therefore he is accounted of according to his breeding.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth in divers promotions created the following Cardinals, beſides many others which dyed, before and after the aſſumption of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth; but eſpecially he gave the Scarlet Gown to the Cardinal <hi>Franciſco Barberino,</hi> his Nephew, in the firſt Conſiſtory that he held.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:115287:26"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XV.</hi> Franceſco Barberino.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Barberino,</hi> a Florentine, and Nephew to the deceaſed Pope <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, the Son of his brother. He was a man, during his Uncles being a Prelate, and a Cardinal, which one would hardly have vouchſafed to ſalute if he had met him in the ſtreets of <hi>Rome;</hi> in ſo poor, and ill a plight he was; he went to ſchool in the Colledge, where he was no better eſteemed of then any one mean Artificers Sonne; ſo that he would have taken it for a great injury if any man had told him that he ſhould have been the Popes Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hew: yet afterwards Fortune, which hath no meaſure in her doings, lifted him up ſo high, as to think of it onely makes people amazed, and beſides themſelves. The Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals ſtood in the Conclave queſtioning about the making of a Pope, and after they had continued there a long time, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing much wearied, they reſolved to elect ſuch a perſon, as not onely was not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of the Papacie, in regard of his young years, but alſo that was not known to be
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:115287:27"/>of too ſtirring and high a ſpirit; inſomuch as they all unanimouſly confeſſed, that when they were in the Conclave they ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thought, nor ever came it into their minds, to aſſume ſuch a perſon to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie: and after he was elected, that old wiſe Cardinal <hi>Creſcentio</hi> cryed out in the ſame Conclave ſo lowd, that every one might hear him, ſaying, we have e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected a piece of a Pope: which words ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily were worthy of conſideration, and how they were afterwards made good in the time of his Papacie, every one may Imagine. At ſuch time as <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth was elected, <hi>Franceſco</hi> and <hi>Antonio</hi> were in the ſchools, when as a great clamor of voices were heard crying out, long live Pope <hi>Urban Barberino,</hi> and at the very ſame inſtant came many Princes, and a world of Caroches to take them from the ſchools, giving them the title of Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, and reverencing them with great ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors. <hi>Franceſco</hi> in the firſt Conſiſtory, which his Holineſs held, was created Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal, and in regard his young age was too unapt for the government, the Pope gave him my Lord <hi>Filomarini</hi> for his Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, but with the title of Maſter of his Chamber, in which place he had ſerved
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:115287:27"/>before the ſame <hi>Urban. Barberino</hi> as ſoon as ſoon as he ſaw himſelf to have attained to the credit of managing affairs, he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred the converſation of <hi>Filomarini,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that he utterly declined it, and began to govern of himſelf, ſo far forth that out of his abſolute arrogance and pride he uſurped the Title of <hi>Cardinale Patrone,</hi> a Title verily which was never heard, nor ever will be heard, to be aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med by any Popes Nephew. Some months after, <hi>Urban</hi> promoted <hi>Antonio</hi> to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown, and then ſent both of them Legates <hi>à Latere, Franceſco</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> and <hi>Antonio</hi> into <hi>France;</hi> and one of them took upon him the protection of the one King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and the other of the other. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco</hi> afterwards had a large penſion from the Catholique King, and made profeſſion of obeying the commands of that Majeſty. <hi>Urban</hi> for ten years together governed ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutely, in which time <hi>Franceſco</hi> had not the power, as one may ſay, to raiſe up a ſtraw from the ground, but thoſe ten years once paſt, <hi>Urban</hi> fell to decline through age, and ſickneſs, and then began he to lift up his head. This Cardinal had nothing elſe good in him but the gratify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a poor man, that in <hi>tomporibus</hi> had
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:115287:28"/>paid for a pot of Wine for him at the Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern, whom he made Yeoman of his Horſe. In the time of his Empire he diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaſted all the Princes; and <hi>inprimis</hi> I may begin with the Emperor <hi>Ferdinand</hi> the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, who upon his election to that State, ſent the Prince of <hi>Egenberg</hi> to <hi>Rome</hi> for his Ambaſſador of obedience to the Pope, where being arrived, that which enſued thereupon is known to every one. The King of <hi>Spain</hi> was ſo affronted by him and his Uncle, as more could not be: for what greater affront can be done to a Crown, then to give for mony, and not other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe, the Scarlet Gown to a deſerve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing perſon; ſuch a one as the Abbot <hi>Pereti</hi> was, unto whom they denyed it, out of the inward hate that they bore him. They lent mony to the <hi>French,</hi> to the end they might make and continue Warre on the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> they gave aid againſt the State of <hi>Milan;</hi> uſed notable deceit in the diſpoſing of <hi>Mantoua</hi> and <hi>Caſale;</hi> cauſed the Marqueſs <hi>de los Velez,</hi> the Catholique Ambaſſador, to be aſſaulted by the <hi>French,</hi> and the Biſhop of <hi>Amega</hi> the Portugal, who by force would have been acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by the Ambaſſador, that reputed him a Rebel; and gave a world of diſguſts
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:115287:28"/>beſides, which to recount would take up a whole year. The King of <hi>France</hi> too, notwithſtanding all the Houſe of <hi>Barberini</hi> ſeem to be well affected to that Crown, hath had his ſhare of diſguſts from them; by delaying the demand of the Hat for the Cardinal <hi>Mazzarino;</hi> by the diſhonor which <hi>Antonio</hi> did to his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties Ambaſſador, in getting his daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter with child under colour of friendſhip, and afterwards poyſoning her, as it is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily believed, at <hi>Caprarola;</hi> inſomuch that the poor Lord not knowing elſe how to be revenged, was fain to ſerve under the command of the Duke of <hi>Parma</hi> in the War againſt the ſaid <hi>Barberini.</hi> Then the diſtaſt which they gave not onely to the Ambaſſador <hi>Coure,</hi> but even to the moſt Chriſtian King himſelf, by cauſing the head of Monſieur <hi>de Ronti,</hi> the ſaid Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadors Kinſman, to be ſtrucken of by the hangman; and laſtly the betraying of that Majeſtie in the Conclave, by helping to promote <hi>Pamphilio</hi> to the Papacie, whom the King deſired to exclude. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over the Internal and External diſguſts, known to all, which they gave to the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> to the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> and to the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:115287:29"/>Republique of <hi>Venice;</hi> by offering to take <hi>Borgo-ſanſepolcro</hi> from the great Duke; by taking from the Duke of <hi>Parma, Caſtro, Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pralo, Ronaglione,</hi> and other States, as alſo indeavouring to take from him likewiſe <hi>Parma,</hi> and <hi>Placentia,</hi> becauſe he would not match with them; by making War on the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> upon their pretenſion to <hi>Comachio;</hi> and on the Republique of <hi>Venice,</hi> for to make them remove out of their Ducal Chamber the antient pictures of their Naval fight and Victory for the reſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution of Pope <hi>Alexander</hi> the ſixth to his former Eſtate. They denyed the King of <hi>Polana</hi> the Hat for Monſieur <hi>Vicconti;</hi> they ſuffered the Cardinal <hi>Orſino</hi> to affront the deceaſed Queen Mother of <hi>France</hi> in the perſon of her Agent; in <hi>Rome</hi> they annihi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lated the Nobility; heheaded the Marqueſs <hi>Manzioli, alias Bentivoglio,</hi> who having been prime Clerke of the Chamber, had reſigned that office, and maried a wife, upon pretext that he had made a book a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> they put to death the Marqueſs <hi>Centini d' Aſcoli in Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>po de fiore,</hi> alledging that he had complot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted againſt the life of the Pope, onely to diſable his Uncle for the Papacie; they ſent <hi>Anarea Caſale</hi> to the Galleys, to the
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:115287:29"/>end his Wealth might come to the Cardinal <hi>Spada,</hi> and other their well-wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers, cauſing him in fifteen daies to be baſtinadoed to death; they baniſhed the Duke of <hi>Cerinto</hi> the State of <hi>Avignon,</hi> upon pretence that he had framed infamous li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bells againſt the old deceaſed Cardinal <hi>Verospi;</hi> they kept <hi>Mario Frangipano</hi> a long time in priſon, although he was a Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier of quality, very old, and in a manner decrepit, and expoſed him to the torture, upon pretence that he had given order for the putting of a fellow to death, that was found hanged in the priſon of a certain Caſtle, notwithſtanding that they which had committed the fact confeſſed pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liquely at the Gallows, how the ſaid Lord was altogether innocent therof; and this they did to no other end, but to force him to leave his eſtate unto them, with this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that he ſhould enjoy it ſo long as he lived, and then it ſhould fall unto the Church; but he would never conſent thereunto, ſaying alwaies thus, <hi>If I be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent let me be freed, if I be not innocent let me be puniſhed;</hi> and had not the War with the Princes of <hi>Italy</hi> hapned, the poor Lord had been made an end of; for then they ſet him at liberty upon condition that he ſhould
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:115287:30"/>ingage himſelf in the war againſt the ſaid Princes. Furthermore they ſought to ruine the Houſe of <hi>Borgheſe,</hi> becauſe they had concluded matrimony with <hi>Donna Olimpia Aldobrandina,</hi> unto whom the Popes eldeſt Nephew was a ſuiter, and for that reaſon they diſgraced them all that ever they could. They deprived <hi>Vittaleſchi,</hi> General of the <hi>Jeſuits,</hi> and <hi>Ridolſi</hi> General of the Dominicans, of their General ſhips, under pretext of ſundry miſdemeanors commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by them. They moſt unjuſtly bereft the ſaid Princes <hi>Borgheſi</hi> of the ſtate of <hi>Mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dola;</hi> and cauſed <hi>Don Paolo Borgheſe,</hi> the Prince his Son, and husband to the ſaid <hi>Donna Aldobrandina,</hi> to be baſely affronted by a common Captain of the watch. They drove a world of poor people, not onely from <hi>Rome,</hi> but alſo out of all the ſtate Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical, and made them go and live in other parts, by reaſon of the grievous taxes and impoſitions which they laid up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them. They cauſed many thouſands of men, that ſerved under their enſignes, to periſh for hunger, whilſt they gave them no pay, and that bread too, which they provided to relieve them, was mixed with chalk, which fretted out the ſoldiers guts, and made them die like doggs. <hi>Innocent</hi>
                  <pb n="49" facs="tcp:115287:30"/>the tenth, in the beginning of his Papacie, was ſo tired with Petitions and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaints againſt <hi>Franceſco</hi> for his injuſtice and extortions, that he cauſed him to be cited to render an accompt of his admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration, which he ſatisfied with his flight into <hi>France.</hi> This Cardinal enjoyed under <hi>Urban</hi> above forty ſeaven Abbacies, and Benefices, with other revenues, the leaſt of which yielded two or three thouſand crowns a year; beſides thoſe that came to thirty thouſand, and forty thouſand, as alſo the Vicechancellorſhip of the Holy Church, which hath eighteen protections of Monaſteries of Nunnes, and Convents of Friers. In ſum he was become a ward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robe of Eccleſiaſtical Benefices; and in the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> things were grown to that paſs, as no man took a ſervant, were it for never ſo vile an Office, unleſs he were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred by this Cardinal <hi>Barberino;</hi> and this he did out of a diabolical policie; for by this means he held correſpondencie with all thoſe, which he had placed as ſpies upon their Maſters, and ſo came to diſcover whatſoever they ſaid, or did. He hath made ſhew of being a wonderous ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt man, and under colour thereof hath deceived I know not how many women.
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:115287:31"/>I think now the world will confeſs there was never any Cardinal that ſo much ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rannized over the Church, and Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom: <hi>&amp; hoc ſufficit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVI.</hi> Erneſto Adalberto d' Arach.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ERneſto Adalberto d' Arach,</hi> is a rich Lord, of the <hi>German</hi> Nation: He was a Prieſt, and promoted by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth to the Scarlet Gown, at the inſtance of the Emperor, in the place of <hi>Pier Luigi Caraffa,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tricario.</hi> This perſon is a man of great parts, &amp; of good life, in regard wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was advanced to the Arch-Biſhoprick of <hi>Prague,</hi> where he hath behaved himſelf much to his own commendation, and the ſatisfaction of all the people there, being highly eſteemed for his good diſpoſition and qualities; howbeit I cannot ſay much of him, becauſe he reſides not in the Court, but continues alwaies at his Church in <hi>Prague,</hi> and therefore not with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out reaſon was it ſaid, when laſt he came to <hi>Rome</hi> a little before the death of <hi>Urban</hi> the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:115287:31"/>eighth, that it was an ill Omen, and a bad ſign, when the <hi>Conſi</hi> were ſeen to approch the Citty, meaning that <hi>Arach</hi> not being wont to come unto <hi>Rome,</hi> his comming now thither was a foretoken of the Popes enſuing death, as accordingly it fell out. This Cardinal is well regarded of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> and as his ſubject, he is, and alwaies will be at his devotion. He is very Charitable, Bountifull, Courteous, Affable, and Friendly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVII.</hi> Giulio Sachetti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIulio Sachetti,</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> the Son of a Merchant, who was partner with the Father of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, whilſt they traded together, being thought to be of kin a far off. The ſaid <hi>Giulio</hi> was made Biſhop of <hi>Gravina,</hi> whether he never went, becauſe he was ſuddainly ſent by <hi>Urban Nuncio</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> where all the time that he exerciſed that charge, he carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf very worthily, and to the great ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of that Crown; wherefore he was promoted by <hi>Urban</hi> to the Scarlet Gown,
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:115287:32"/>as likewiſe were all the other Nuntioes, except <hi>Caraffa.</hi> He was much eſteemed of by <hi>Urban,</hi> who conferred on him many benefits and graces, making him alſo Kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of the Seal of Juſtice, which he ſtill exerciſeth. He is a Lord of great merit, and the <hi>Barberini</hi> thought without all doubt to have created him in the paſt Conclave Pope; but they failed in their purpoſe, whilſt by the power of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> faction he was excluded, not becauſe he was not a deſerving perſon, but in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard he was too much affected and obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to the ſaid <hi>Barberini:</hi> Others ſay he was excluded, for that upon the aſſembly of a Congregation touching the receiving of the Ambaſſador of the King of <hi>Portugal,</hi> he had ſhewed himſelf inclined to receive him; as alſo by reaſon he was too great a friend to <hi>Mazzarino,</hi> who had been a follower of his, ſo as neceſſarily he would have been an Enemy and depreſſor of the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and would have followed the ſtepps of <hi>Urban.</hi> He is of an exemplary life, Charitable, Pleaſant, and Rich, but not very Liberal, for, as a <hi>Florentine,</hi> he is ſomewhat penurious, and niggardly. He hath two Brothers, <hi>Mattheo</hi> and <hi>Aleſſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dro,</hi> whereof the firſt hath to wife a Lady
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:115287:32"/>of the Houſe of <hi>Rocellai,</hi> a Family amongſt the <hi>Florentines</hi> ſufficiently <hi>French;</hi> and he hath many Sonnes: the ſecond hath ſerv'd in the Warres of <hi>Flanders</hi> under the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique King. <hi>Mattheo;</hi> at ſuch time as the Sea was vacant, was qualified with a title of the Church by <hi>Barberino,</hi> who held <hi>Sachetti</hi> certainly for Pope, as in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner did <hi>Mattheo,</hi> inſomuch that he cauſed the Cellar of his Palace to be ſet open for every body to drink as much Wine as he would for joy: whereupon, after they had well drunk, they cryed out publiquely, <hi>long live Pope Sachetti;</hi> but when as after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he ſaw that <hi>Pamphilio</hi> was made Pope, for very ſpight and rage he fell madd: And thus may every one judge, if <hi>Sachetti</hi> had been Pope, what a confuſion there would have been in the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, and in what a condition the State Eccleſiaſtical would have been; for through their avarice they would have ruined all. The greateſt confident <hi>Sachetti</hi> hath, is thought to be the Cardinal <hi>Falconi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eri,</hi> now Legate of <hi>Bologna,</hi> who was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted by <hi>Urban</hi> at the inſtance of the ſaid <hi>Sachetti,</hi> after his return from being Nuncio in <hi>Flanders,</hi> from whence he was excluded by the Cardinal <hi>Infante,</hi> for that he knew
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:115287:33"/>him to be too much <hi>French. Sachetti</hi> hath divers times murmured againſt the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of Monarchy; whence he was held by the Regal Miniſters to be aliena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted from deſiring the felicity of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrian</hi> Family, which hath done him but little good. The greateſt obſtacle he hath had, and hath, is the great Duke, who ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving found Pope <hi>Barberino</hi> little available to him, ſeeks with all his power to keep any Vaſſal of his from comming to the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie, and therefore <hi>Sachetti</hi> will never at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain unto it, although the <hi>Spaniards</hi> ſhould concur with him; which is unlikely, not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withſtanding he ſeems to be devoted to <hi>Spain,</hi> whereas indeed he is contrary unto it; but I ſhould judge the Catholique King to be directly out of his wits, if ever he concur with him more, ſeeing he was the confident Counſellor firſt of <hi>Antonio</hi>'s, and afterwards <hi>Franceſco</hi>'s and <hi>Tadeo</hi>'s flight into <hi>France.</hi> At the end of the Conclave a writing came forth, intituled the paſſion of <hi>Sachetti,</hi> beginning thus, <hi>Paſſio Domini noſtri ſecundum Matthaeum;</hi> which to avoid prolixity I will omit, the rather too be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſerves not for our purpoſe. Ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther writing alſo came forth, which
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:115287:33"/>ſaid, <hi>He that entred Pope, came out Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XVIII.</hi> Bernardino Spada.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>BErnardino Spada,</hi> a native of <hi>Briſighella,</hi> of an ordinary Family, being diſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded of Colliers. He put himſele into the Prelacie, and was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eigth exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſed in many Charges, and then ſent into <hi>France,</hi> where he reſided a good while, and ſpent there a great part of his Patrimony. <hi>Urban,</hi> knowing his merits, promoted him to the Scarlet Gown, the rather becauſe in his Nuntioes place he had carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to the ſatisfaction of both parts. He is a perſon of great abilities, is well verſt in all manner of Negotiations, and is an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Stateſman. He was picked out and choſen by <hi>Uban</hi> the eighth, as a man of Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and worth, to compoſe the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences depending between him and the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> who was come with a great Army to the confines of the Eccleſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical State. and had ſeazed on divers Lands and Caſtles of the Apoſtolick Sea,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:115287:34"/>and in particular <hi>Aquapendente,</hi> where the ſaid Duke had intrenched himſelf: In front of whom ſtood <hi>Antonio</hi> with an Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my of twelve thouſand foot, and four thouſand horſe to keep him from over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>running the Eccleſiaſtical State; and <hi>Spada</hi> was ſent with the title of Plenipotentiary, to conclude an agreement: He went, act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and returned, but was by <hi>Urban</hi> very ill rewarded; for after he had concluded, and ſigned the Capitulations of the ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cord, wherein the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> the Republique of <hi>Venice,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> intervened as mediators, <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban,</hi> ſeeing the Duke departed, and gone to his States of <hi>Parma</hi> and <hi>Placentia,</hi> decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſaid Capitulations <hi>null,</hi> and inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid; ſaying that <hi>Spada motu proprio,</hi> and without his conſent, had ſigned them. Herewith the aforeſaid Princes held them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves juſtly offended, and ſeeing the Pope leavy ſoldiers to ſend againſt the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> each of thoſe Princes took up arms to defend him. But Cardinal <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da,</hi> beholding his reputation blemiſhed in this ſort, without any fear at all publiſhed a <hi>Manifeſt</hi> of his Reaſons, ſaying, that all that he had done, and capitulated, was with his Holineſs, goodwill and appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:115287:34"/>When the world plainly ſaw that the poor Cardinal had no way faulted, but had exactly obſerved the command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of the Pope, he was by all men pit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied: but the Warre which enſued there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon with the ſpilling of ſo much blood, was that which cleared the buſineſs, and brought the Cardinal into greater credit then before; for in proceſs of time the Pope was fain with the damage of the holy Church, and his own reputation, to make a peace, with giving full ſatisfaction to the pretendants, which had made Warre in divers places; and in particular the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan</hi> on <hi>Perugia</hi> ſide, and the Duke of <hi>Parma,</hi> the Republique of <hi>Venice,</hi> and the Duke of <hi>Modena,</hi> in the <hi>Bologneſe.</hi> This Cardinal is no great friend to the Houſe of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> for the cauſes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-mentioned. <hi>Spada</hi> is obſtinately devo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted o the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> quite contrary to the Cardinal <hi>Rocci</hi> his Kinſman, who is altogether for the <hi>Spaniard.</hi> In the paſt Conclave he laboured much for the electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, and therfore is well regarded of him. This Cardinal is a great perſon, hath a wiſe head, and is full of high thoughts. He is a Poet, an Hiſtorian, and a Polititian, ſo that he will leave all
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:115287:35"/>the paſtime of the world for to ſtudy. He was one that inherited the greateſt part of the ſtate of <hi>Andrea Caſale</hi> the <hi>Bolognoſe,</hi> and was alſo the principal inſtrument of his ignominious death in the Galleyes; but God, as a juſt Judge, will not leave ſuch a wickedneſs unpuniſhed. Now becauſe there are many that have not been made acquainted with this doubtful Hiſtory, &amp; may be deſirous to know it, I will not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the relation of it as ſuccinctly as I can. <hi>Andrea Caſale,</hi> the Son of a rich and Noble Senator of <hi>Bologna,</hi> his Father being dead, remained a child under the Government of his Mother, together with two Siſters which were made Nunnes. This <hi>Andrea,</hi> being come to mans Eſtate, and full of ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neroſity and ſpirit, thought it too baſe a thing for him to live drown'd in idleneſs and delights; wherefore he reſolved, though againſt his Mothers will, to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Hungary,</hi> and there for the acquiring of fame to ſerve the Emperor in his Warres againſt the <hi>Turk,</hi> as accordingly he did: And being arrived in <hi>Hungary,</hi> had the Charge of a Captain of a Troop of Horſe conferred on him. Now it happened cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain months after, that the <hi>Turkes</hi> gave the Emperors forces a great defeat, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:115287:35"/>many Lords were ſlain, and many were made priſoners, and in particular the ſaid Signor <hi>Andrea Caſale.</hi> The report of this defeat being ſpread over all <hi>Italy,</hi> they that pretended to the inheritance of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drea</hi>'s eſtate were very deſirous to know whither he we alive, or dead; whereupon divers <hi>Bologneſe</hi> ſoldiers being returned to <hi>Bologna,</hi> whether it were that they were ſuborned with money, as for ſome other end, they gave out that the ſaid <hi>Andrea Caſale</hi> was dead; and further they made Affidavit, that they had ſeen him dead, and alſo had buried him with their own hands. In the mean time the poor Cava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lier remained in the hands of the <hi>Turkes,</hi> and continually wrote letters unto his Mother, to ſend mony for the ranſoming of him; which letters for the moſt part fell into the hands of thoſe, that pretended to the inheriting of his eſtate, and were ſtill by them ſecretly burnt: Nevertheleſs it could not chuſe but that ſome of them ſhould come unto his Mother, who with great joy imparted them to their kinred, by whom ſhe was condemned for a fooliſh and imprudent old woman, telling her that her Son <hi>Andrea</hi> was dead, and that thoſe letters were forged by ſome one,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:115287:36"/>that meant to cheat her; ſo the good Lady; being put of in this manner, at length dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with grief, and, after many years, it was the will of God, that the poor Signior was redeemed by the holy Company of the Trinity, with many other men, and women, who were, as it were in tryumph, all clad in white, conducted after a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion manner to <hi>Rome;</hi> where being arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, the poor Cavalier knew not which way to turn himſelf: but God, which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver abandons any, made him call to mind, how one <hi>Giovanni Antonio,</hi> who had for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly received many curteſies from him at <hi>Bologna,</hi> was at that inſtant Captain of the watch in <hi>Rome;</hi> wherefore he went un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, and having acquainted him with his fortunes, the Captain, moved with pity to ſee a perſon of that quality reduced to ſuch termes; and very well knowing him to be the true <hi>Andrea Caſale,</hi> aſſigned him a Caroach, with two Lackies, and forty Crowns a month; which after he had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued unto him for the ſpace of ſeaven or eight weeks, he brought him to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the Pope, who received him very graciouſly, and ſhewed to be glad of his recovered liberty; little thinking then that he himſelf ſhould be he, that afterwards
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:115287:36"/>ſhould not onely deprive him of liberty, but of his life alſo. <hi>Andrea</hi> having infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med his Holineſs, how all his eſtate had been ſeized upon, and was wrongfully poſſeſſed by others, humbly beſought him to doe him that grace and juſtice, as to reſtore him to his own againe; which the Pope had a good intention to grant: whereupon he commenced a ſuit againſt them that had gotten his eſtate, who came running with all ſpeede to the Court, to oppoſe him, and proved that <hi>Andrea Caſale</hi> was dead, and that this was a meere coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terfit, and an impoſtor; wherefore Signior <hi>Andrea</hi> was conſtrained to become a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, and ſo to defend himſelf, and prove, that he was the true <hi>Andrea Caſale.</hi> His Holineſs cauſed a proceſs thereof to bee framed in the City of <hi>Bologna,</hi> where the nurſe that gave him ſuck then lived, who upon her examination averred that he had a certain marke upon his left ſhoulder, which upon ſearch was accordingly found there; beſides divers other teſtimonies, that manifeſted, he was the true <hi>Andrea.</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinall <hi>Spada,</hi> ſeeing the matter goe ſo ill on his ſide, ſought with fraud to beguile him, and gave him to underſtand, that if he would deſiſt from his ſuite, and revoke
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:115287:37"/>all his pretenſions, he would aſſign him a Caroach with four ſervants, and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newes yearly, able to maintain him like a Cavalier, as long as he lived: Which <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drea</hi> hearing, cryed out publiquely, ſaying: <hi>Either I am</hi> Andrea Caſale, <hi>and will have all that is mine; or I am not he, and will have no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</hi> This comming to the knowledge of <hi>Spada,</hi> he went as it were in a deſperate moode to the Pope, and ſo earneſtly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought him not to ſuffer his, and many o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Families, amongſt whom the inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance of <hi>Andrea Caſale</hi> was diſtributed, to be undone by takeing the ſame from them, that his Holineſs, I know not how, did moſt unjuſtly, not onely not put him in Poſſeſſion of his eſtate, but wickedly ſent him to the Galleys; where, leaſt upon change of the Pope he might ſet a foot his claim anew, Cardinal <hi>Spada</hi> wrought in ſuch ſort with the Commanders of the Galleyes, that in the ſpace of fifteen daies he was baſtinadoed to death. A caſe veri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly worthy of compaſſion, and the mishap of this poor infortunate Cavalier deſerves for example ſake to be publiſhed to all the World; his death being bewailed not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly by the common people, but by all the Nobility of <hi>Rome,</hi> and <hi>Bologna.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:115287:37"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XIX.</hi> Federico Carnaro.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FEderico Cornaro,</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Venice;</hi> he was Biſhop of <hi>Vicenza</hi> in <hi>Lombardie,</hi> and afterwards was made Biſhop of <hi>Padon.</hi> He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown at the inſtance of his Rebublique, as a man deſerving, and of a good life. He is ſixty years of age, or thereabout; wherefore he pretends much to <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, and it will not be hard for him to attain thereunto, being devoted as he is to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> whereof not onely he, but his whole Family makes open profeſſion; his Country alone may be contrary, and an obſtacle unto him: He is a perſon of no mean underſtanding, Affable and Courte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, and is therefore much eſteemed of by the ſacred Colledge. He hath divers Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hews, who are little ſeen in the Court; but the eldeſt of them, at ſuch time as his Uncle was Biſhop of <hi>Padoa,</hi> led a moſt wicked &amp; diſſolute life in <hi>Rome,</hi> which was accompanied with ſo infinite a pride, that it was able, as one may ſay, to cauſe ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:115287:38"/>fall of Angels from Heaven; And this alone will be enough to keep <hi>Cornaro</hi> farre from the Papacie; otherwiſe he hath no defects of any conſideration, being chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, and worthy of all Honor. The Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Cornari</hi> is one of the principal of that Republique, having had many Dukes, and Senators iſſued from it, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a Queen of <hi>Cyprus,</hi> who gave that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to the <hi>Venetians,</hi> by which dona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion they held it a long time. He reſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Biſhoprick of <hi>Padoa,</hi> and had the Patriarchſhip of <hi>Venice,</hi> which after ſome years he alſo reſigned. He is much eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of his Republique, although there hath paſt ſome diſguſts between them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="20" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:115287:38"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XX.</hi> Martio Ginetti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArtio Ginetti,</hi> born in the Citty of <hi>Veletri,</hi> of vile deſcent, the Son of a common Artificer: He came to <hi>Rome</hi> in the beginning of the creation of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, where he courted divers Cardinals, and in the end putting himſelf into the Prelacy, he got into the favour of the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Franceſco Barberino,</hi> who brought him into ſuch credit with the Pope his Uncle, that he held him in great eſteem, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted him to the Scarlet Gown, to the end he ſhould acknowledge no other de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendancie, then that of the houſe of <hi>Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini.</hi> His holineſs enriched him with many benefices, and made him Vicar of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie; which Office is during life; he made him alſo Protector of the whole order of the <hi>Carmelites,</hi> and cauſed him to lodge continually in the Apoſtolical Palace. Now becauſe he was altogether unknown to Princes, and was of no account abroad, the <hi>Barberini</hi> reſolved to illuſtrate him in the ſight of the World, and ſo ſent him Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gate into <hi>Germany</hi> to treat of a univerſal
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:115287:39"/>peace, to the end all Chriſtendom might acknowledge him for the principal inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the publique good; but the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>happy iſſue of that his charge ſhewed his ignorance rather, and imprudence, ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring himſelf ridiculous in ſo ſublime an employment, whereby he no way profited Chriſtendom, but exceedingly profited himſelf and his Houſe; for living very ſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ringly, he purſed up the moſt part of that great entertainment which was aſſigned him for his Legateſhip: In his return back towards <hi>Rome,</hi> and as he was upon the way, there was ſent him by an expreſs poſt to <hi>Ferrara</hi> a Grant of the Legates place of that Citty, where he heaped up no little riches; and after his arrival at <hi>Rome,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Capucino</hi> paid him all the profits accruing of his Vicarſhiſh by him admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred in his abſence. This Cardinal hath given to his Kinſmen all the Offices and Dignities that poſſibly he can: He is not very learned, although he hath taken great pains in ſtudying. The <hi>Barberini</hi> will never nominate him in the Conclave, for they are ſure it will not ſucceed, in regard he is known to be too much their partial obligee. He is but little reſpected in the ſacred Colledge, though by reaſon of his
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:115287:39"/>age he is capable of being Pope. Whoſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver looks upon the houſe of this Cardinal, will alwaies behold it void of all reſort, none going thither but thoſe which have buſineſs appertaining to the Vicarſhip, and that are of neceſſity to paſs thorough his hands; ſo that one ſhall never ſee any viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant Coches there, he being no otherwiſe accounted of, then as of a forelorn Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal. He ſhews himſelf to be no way depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding on any of the Princes, out of the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſion he hath to the Papacie; and albeit he was Lagate <hi>à Latere</hi> with the Emperor for the univerſal peace, as aforeſaid, yet is he not for all that devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> becauſe he, being wholly depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on the <hi>Barberini,</hi> will, as ſuch, be all<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies <hi>French,</hi> if not openly, at leaſtwiſe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly. His behaviour is familiar and fleg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matick, ſeeming to favour every one, and is of an indifferent good nature, but me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lancholick.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="21" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="89" facs="tcp:115287:40"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXI.</hi> Don Antonio Barberino.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>DON Antonio Barberino,</hi> the crook<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>back, Nephew to <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, and the brother of <hi>Franceſco</hi> and <hi>Tadeo;</hi> he was born in <hi>Rome,</hi> and therefore intitles himſelf a <hi>Roman.</hi> He was by the Pope crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prior of the great Croſs of <hi>Malta,</hi> with an intention not to make him a Cardinal, it ſeeming ſufficient unto him, that he had already promoted to that dignity <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco</hi> his eldeſt Nephew, and the Capuchin his brother; but <hi>Antonio</hi> ſo importuned his Uncle, that at length he promoted him alſo to the Scarlet Gown, which above all things he he was ambitious of. This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal was even from his birth ever bounti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and hath with donatives and mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nanimitie drawn many to his devotion, inſomuch that although he hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed ſome errors and exceſſes, yet is he not therefore ſo rigorouſly envyed, whilſt be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing poſſeſt of the goods of fortune he hath alſo made others partakers thereof, and hath prodigally ſpent his own. He hath
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:115287:40"/>not been a little taken with the beauties of women, on whom he hath waſted great ſummes of Gold: <hi>La Checa Buffona in tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus</hi> was his Miſtriſs, who out of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence that ſhe had in the protection of the Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> went up and down maſked in the Carneval time, for which the Governor of <hi>Rome</hi> cauſed her without any reſpect at all to be whipped thorough the City. He got with child the Daughter of the Marqueſs of <hi>Couré,</hi> Ambaſſador of <hi>France:</hi> To a <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Curteſan, which dwelt in the <hi>Giulian</hi> ſtreet, he gave for the firſt time a thouſand crownes: but, not to ſay more, this alone ſhall ſerve for a clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing up of ſo many indignities this Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal hath committed, that to a Pedant, which had the charge of a very fair boy, the Sonne of a Gentleman, whom he let him enjoy ſeveral times, he gave for a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward thereof a Biſhoprick, <hi>nella Marca di Marcantonio.</hi> I will not ſpeak of his bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dache, whom being but the Sonne of a barber, he hath reduced to ſuch a paſs, as not content with having inriched him, he hath cauſed him to be adorned with the title of a Marqueſs. The ſaid Cardinal was ſent Legate Apoſtolical, and <hi>Generaliſſimo,</hi> into the States of <hi>Bologna, Ferrara,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magna,</hi>
                  <pb n="70" facs="tcp:115287:41"/>againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> where he caried himſelf valiantly, and with the ſatisfaction not onely of all thoſe people, but alſo of the ſouldierie; and if any one hath traduced his good name, ſaying, that he was privy to the death of the convert Nunnes of <hi>Magdalens</hi> in <hi>Bologna,</hi> he lies; for <hi>Antonio</hi> was not of Councel with that fact; but indeed after the Delinquents were diſcovered, in ſtead of chaſtiſing, he favoured and protected them, the one being <hi>Carlo Poſcente,</hi> and the other <hi>Manente</hi> his Secretary; nay more, he ſent <hi>Carlo Poſcente</hi> for his Vice-Duke into the ſtate of <hi>Segni,</hi> and alſo kept the Archbiſhop of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logna</hi> from proceeding againſt them, enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning him to ſpeak no more thereof. I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not deny but <hi>Antonio</hi> committed an er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror in having ſo little regard to his repu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; for as Legate Apoſtolical <hi>à Latere,</hi> as General, and as the Popes Nephew, he might with all rigor have taken infor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation of the matter, and then arraigned and condemned them to the puniſhment, which the heynouſneſs of their offence requited, and afterwards he might graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly have pardoned them; for ſo he had ſhewed himſelf a juſt Judge, and they too, as if they had been ſufficiently chaſtiſed,
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:115287:41"/>had not incurred that, which after the death of the Pope his Uncle, arrived unto them; being both of them firſt confined unto his Palace, and after that ſent pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoners to <hi>Bologna,</hi> where they were put to death; &amp; <hi>Antonio</hi> himſelf was neceſſitated to fly into <hi>France,</hi> very much pittied by moſt men, whereas every one wiſhed all the miſchief they could deviſe to <hi>Franceſco,</hi> and <hi>Tadeo.</hi> This Cardinal is Chamberlain of the holy Church, Archprieſt <hi>della Baſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica diſanta Maria Maggiore,</hi> hath many Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bacies and Protections, and will alwaies be at the devotion of the <hi>French</hi> King, by whom he is defended, and protected in theſe his misfortunes; but it is believed, that he is now returned again into the Popes favor by the mediation of the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:115287:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Girolamo Colonna.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIrolamo Colonna,</hi> of the Title <hi>di Santo Euſtachio,</hi> and of a moſt antient and noble <hi>Roman</hi> family, which hath had ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Popes, and a world of Cardinals. He was promoted to the Scarlet Cown by <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> the eighth, together with Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> at the inſtance of the Prince Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect, of <hi>Donna Anna Barberina,</hi> and of the Conſtable, in regard of the affinitie, that was contracted between them. This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal is richly furniſhed with the goods of fortune, and eſtates; he is underſtanding, prudent; well eſteemed of in the Court, and reverenced in the ſacred Colledge, both for his blood, and wiſedom: And his carriage doth not diſpleaſe, although he goes proudly, and ſtately through the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, like another <hi>Martin</hi> the fifth; but withall he is courteous, honours every one, is exceeding liberal, and well affected to the Pope, who therefore loves him, as alſo for that he was very partial in his e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection. <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth made him Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop of <hi>Bologna,</hi> which Archbiſhoprick,
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:115287:42"/>after he had held it certain years, he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigned in the time of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth unto my Lord <hi>Albergati,</hi> a <hi>Bologneſe</hi> Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman, who is now a Cardinal, by the name of <hi>Lodoviſio Colonna.</hi> Albeit the <hi>Colo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſi</hi> and the <hi>Barberini</hi> have matched toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, yet have there no effects of friend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip paſt betwixt them for divers private intereſts: Neither are the <hi>Coloneſi</hi> any great friends to the Houſe of the <hi>Gaetani,</hi> alſo a moſt antient and noble <hi>Roman</hi> family; for that <hi>Don Gregorio Gaetano,</hi> the brother of the Duke of <hi>Sermoneta,</hi> and Uncle of the Prince of <hi>Caſerta,</hi> was in a manner treache<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rouſly killed by <hi>Don Carlo Colonna;</hi> who for that fact was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth condem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to death, and afterwards pardoned, to the end no future Pope ſhould take any further cognizance of that cauſe; and to ſave his life, that was in danger by reaſon of that enmity, he made himſelf a fryer of the order of Saint <hi>Benedict,</hi> and then was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth preferred to be Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhop <hi>in partibus infidelium.</hi> The ſaid Houſe of <hi>Colonna</hi> likewiſe doth not much love the Houſe of the <hi>Ceſarini,</hi> although the occaſion of <hi>Don Gregorio Gaetanoe's</hi> death proceeded from <hi>Don Carlo</hi> his defending the reputation of the Duke <hi>Ceſarino</hi> his
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:115287:43"/>Nephew, who being under age, pretended that he had received an affront from the ſaid <hi>Gregorio Gaetano,</hi> in making him by force to ſtay in his way, that his Caroach might have the precedence. The Houſe of the Conſtable <hi>Colonna</hi> holds little correſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pondence with the houſe of the Prince of <hi>Galliclano,</hi> and of the Prince of <hi>Carbognano, alias</hi> Duke of <hi>Baſſanella,</hi> all of the houſe of <hi>Colonna;</hi> who though they be all ſprung out of one ſtock, yet doth each of them pretend to be better, then the other, for the preheminence: the truth is, that the houſe of the Prince of <hi>Carbognano</hi> is the right family, derived from <hi>Sciano Colonna;</hi> and therefore with reaſon is the <hi>Piatza,</hi> where his Palace is ſcitunted, called the <hi>Piatza</hi> of <hi>Sciana.</hi> Theſe Lords at firſt were all for the Catholique Crown, but upon the matching of the Conſtable <hi>Colonnaes</hi> Houſe with the Pope, the <hi>Spaniards</hi> for their own intereſt honoured them with ſuch Titles, and States, as the Duke of of <hi>Baſſanello,</hi> of a differing Houſe, was therewith to diſtaſted, that he ſet up the ames of the moſt Chriſtian King, and took to wife the baſe daughter of the Duke of <hi>Parma.</hi> The Prince of <hi>Gallieano</hi> was made a priſoner at <hi>Naples,</hi> upon pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:115287:43"/>of rebellion, a little before the riſing of that people, for that there were many ſaddles, armes, and much ammunition found in his Caſtles, which he poſſeſſed in the Province of <hi>Abruzzo:</hi> and whilſt all things ſeemed to be compoſed, and that he was ready to be abſolved, and ſet at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertie, a new conſpiracie of divers Princes and Barons of the Kingdom of <hi>Naples</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Catholique King was diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, amongſt whom the Prince of <hi>Gallica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no</hi> was included; for a certain <hi>Neapoletan</hi> Apoſtate <hi>Theatin,</hi> named <hi>Andrea Paolucci,</hi> being intercepted and apprehended with letters about him to ſeveral <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Lords from <hi>France,</hi> and put to the torture, named many, and in particular the ſaid Prince of <hi>Gallicano.</hi> The Conſtable alſo, brother to the Cardinal, was not long ſince, at ſuch time as <hi>Gallicano</hi> was a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoner, ſummoned by the Vice-Roy to come to <hi>Naples,</hi> and he put himſelf in the way to have gone thither, but in the midſt of his journey he returned, and in his ſtead ſent a gentleman of his family to feign that he was ſo indiſpoſed in his health, as he could not come himſelf: for had he gone in perſon, I am perſwaded he likewiſe would have fallen into the ſame
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:115287:44"/>labyrinth. This Houſe hath ever been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voted to that of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> and the preſent Cardinal will alwaies be of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction, if diſguſts do not ariſe from new diſcoveries. He is a haughty Lord, and ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſenſible, inſomuch as he was for a good while diſtaſted with the old Cardinal <hi>de Medici</hi> about precedence; but the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences between them were compoſed by <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, immediately upon his creation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="22" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXII.</hi> Cirriaco Rocci.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CIrriaco Rocci,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> his Original de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcent was from the City of <hi>Cremona</hi> in the ſtate of <hi>Milan;</hi> He was a Prelate, &amp; ſent <hi>Nuntio</hi> by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth to the Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rors Majeſtie, after which he promoted him to the Scarlet Gown. This Cardinal in not very intelligent, but ſeeemes to know much; he is an old man, pretends greatly to the Papacie, and is not aſhamed to ſpeak of it to every one, promiſing in that caſe, Dignities, Graces, and Favors.
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:115287:44"/>In the laſt Conclave he indeavoured much for his exaltation thereunto, repoſing all his hopes in the hands of Cardinal <hi>Spada,</hi> his kinſman; but for all that he would not propound him, knowing full well, that for his reſpect he would have been excluded, and ſo he ſhould have had his fortune diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compoſed for the future, as the <hi>Barberini</hi> did in the perſon of <hi>Sachetti:</hi> and the reaſon of it is, that if <hi>Rocci</hi> were Pope, the ſaid Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal <hi>Spada</hi> would command all; who is not much deſired of any, and in particular ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horred of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> becauſe they know him to be of a too ſtirring, and fantaſtical a humor. He hath one Nephew, that is the Abbot <hi>Rocci,</hi> who would be he, that ſhould reign; but in regard of his young years he would not be fit for the Government. He is a very affable Lord, of a good life, and moſt devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king open profeſſion thereof; wherefore he will alwaies be <hi>Spaniſh,</hi> though he be the <hi>Barberinies</hi> creature. He is well regarded of the preſent Pope <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="24" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:115287:45"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIV.</hi> Giovanni Battiſta Palotta.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIovanni Battiſta Palotta,</hi> is of an honeſt family of the little Country of <hi>Calde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rola nella Marca:</hi> He is Nephew to the late Cardinal <hi>Palotta,</hi> unto whom he is no way inferior, and is well accommodated with the goods of fortune; for the Cardinal his Uncle left him a great eſtate. Having put himſelf into the Prelacie, he was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth exerciſed in divers Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges, and in particular was made Lord Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernor of <hi>Rome,</hi> wherein he carried him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with much integrity, and to the great ſatisfaction of the people, being ſevere, and ſo upright, that in point of juſtice he made no reckoning of his Holineſs Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hewes. For whereas it was the cuſtome a little before the Carnival time to make proclamation, that no woman whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſhould during the ſaid Carnival goe thorough the Courſe masked, on pain of being whipped, or ſuffring ſome ſuch o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther puniſhment, as to the Governor ſhould ſeem meet, the famous <hi>Checa Buffo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na</hi> was ſeen going in that time thorough
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:115287:45"/>the Courſe masked; and albeit ſhe was oftentimes admoniſhed to forbear doing ſo, yet would ſhe not deſiſt. Whereat <hi>Palot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ta</hi> being diſpleaſed, cauſed her ſuddainly to be impriſoned, and then having or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained that ſhe ſhould be publiquely whipped thorough the City, to avoid the interceſſions, that might be made to him in her behalf, he ſhut himſelf up in his Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>binet, and gave order to his ſervants not to come at him, or diſturb him, during the ſpace of two houres, for any cauſe, or meſſage whatſoever, but that they ſhould in the mean time entertain thoſe that came to ſpeak with him; whereupon arri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved a Gentleman from Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> who kept a great coil to ſpeak with the ſaid <hi>Palotta,</hi> the Governor; but he was put of with good words untill the prefixed time was paſt, and then he was admitted to the preſence of the Governor, unto whom he brought an order from Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> for the ſpeedy ſetting at liberty of the ſaid <hi>Checa Buffona. Palotta</hi> anſwered, that his Eminencie ſhould be obeyed, and preſently made a Warrant for the releaſing of her out of priſon; but when it came thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Checa</hi> had already been whipped tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough the City; which <hi>Antonio</hi> underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:115287:46"/>took on like a mad man, and mightily threatned to be revenged. <hi>Palotta,</hi> fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeeing the danger he was likely to incur, acquainted the Pope with the buſineſs, who commended him for that he had done; but his Holineſſe, knowing well, that <hi>Antonio</hi> was wreakful, and vindica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, to take away the inconvenience, that might ariſe upon that occaſion, deprived <hi>Palotta</hi> of his Government, and ſent him Collector into the Kingdome of <hi>Portugal;</hi> where having remained ſome months; he took upon him to maintain certain Ecceſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſtical jurisdictions, and excommunica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted all the Royal Councell of the City of <hi>Lisbon,</hi> for which he was forced to leape out of a window to ſave himſelf by flight towards <hi>Rome;</hi> and there being arrived, he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown for divers reſpects. The firſt was, for the merit of his labors, his Holineſs knowing him to be a man of great abilities and knowledge; and the ſecond, for to ſhield him from the malice of <hi>Antonio,</hi> who for all that, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with his brother <hi>Franceſco,</hi> hath given him hundreds of diſguſts, continually contrarying him in the cauſe and ſuite de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending between the General of the <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtinian</hi> Order, and the ſaid <hi>Palotta,</hi> who
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:115287:46"/>deſired to have chaſtiſed him for divers miſdemeanors committed by him in his place; and <hi>Antonio,</hi> to croſſe <hi>Palotta,</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tected and defended him, and in the end to deſpight him, got him by an Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal brieve to be confirmed in the General<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip for ſeaven years more, beſides many other abuſes no way deſerved by the ſaid Cardinal, who is a perſon capable of the Papacie, and <hi>Rome</hi> would be happy if he ſhould come to be Pope, that ſo it might ſee the pride of the <hi>Barberini</hi> brought down. If he lives to ſome vacant Sea, he may attain thereunto; for he is much eſteemed of, and reputed very deſerving by all the Princes, unto whom his vertues, merits, and excellent qualities are well known; beſides, he is highly regarded by <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, the now reigning Pope; but for his too free ſpeech no ſmall hatred was conceived againſt him by ſome of his Holineſſe principal kindred; for he was one day deſired by the Pope, to tell him, what was ſaid of him in <hi>Rome;</hi> and <hi>Palotta</hi> anſwered, <hi>Bleſſed Father, all the City murmures at your Siſter-in-law the Lady</hi> Olimpia<hi>'s too fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quent comming to, and abiding in the Palace;</hi> whereunto the Pope replyed, <hi>well, we will remedy it;</hi> and the next time <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi>
                  <pb n="82" facs="tcp:115287:47"/>came to him, he told her what <hi>Palotta</hi> had ſaid, and therefore deſired her to forbear comming ſo often to the Apoſtolical Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lace. Hereupon <hi>Donna Olimpia</hi> took ſuch a ſpleen againſt the ſaid <hi>Palotta,</hi> that meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him upon a time, ſhe drew the Cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of her Caroach againſt the very face of him; which <hi>Palotta</hi> ſeeing, begged leave of his Holineſſe to go unto <hi>Calderola</hi> his Country, about ſome affairs that he had there, and gave it out in the Court, that he went to viſit the Fortreſſe of <hi>Marina nella Marca.</hi> His Votes, as well in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, as in the Conſiſtory, are great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed: He hath no Enemy, nor any that is contrary to him: He honors all, and where he can do any ſervice, he doth it willingly: he is affable in entertainment, leades an holy and retired life, loves not light converſations, and is very ſtudious. He hath many Nephews, whereof one is in <hi>Flanders,</hi> another was a ſtudent in <hi>Bolog<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na',</hi> where he ſlew a ſcholler that was his Rival, for which his Uncle cares not much for him; but his darling is he that is in the Engliſh Colledge, who is a youth reaſonably well learned, and that in caſe he ſhould become Pope, would be he that ſhall reign. This Cardinal is not of any
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:115287:47"/>faction, but he is thought to be devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Austria.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> Theodoro Trivultio.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>THeodoro Trivultio,</hi> of a moſt noble fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the City of <hi>Milan;</hi> he was a Prince, and had a wife, by whom he had children; but after her death he reſigned his Principality to his eldeſt Son, and went to <hi>Rome,</hi> where puting himſelf into the Prelacie, he bought the Clerk of the Chambers place, and after ſome years he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown by <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban</hi> the eighth, both to make mony by the ſale of that Office, and alſo to ſhew that he would promote a vaſſal of the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique King. This Cardinal merited the Hat as he was a Prince, yet was he fain to make uſe of the Prelacie before he could attain unto it. He is a good ſoldier, and is much beloved and reverenced by the King of <hi>Spain,</hi> being reputed the moſt faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full <hi>Italian</hi> Vaſſal, that he hath; for when he ſees that his Majeſties Miniſters in the State of <hi>Milan</hi> do not behave themſelves
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:115287:48"/>with that fidelity as they ought, he ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily advertiſes the Catholique King of it. He is not very rich, but is alwaies ſupply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed as he hath occaſion by his ſaid Majeſty. At ſuch time as he lived in the Court, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the aſſumption of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, he ſhewed himſelf very bountiful, ſo farre as he was able; but he contracted many debts, which before his departure from the Court he ſatisfied very punctually. He uſed to go up and down the City with a great and ſtately train, but to ſpeak with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out paſſion, there was much boaſt, but litle roſt. He could not part from the Court ſo ſoon, as he purpoſed to have done, for want of mony, and therefore he was fain to ſtay the comming of four thouſand crownes from <hi>Naples</hi> which were ſent him by the Vice-Roy: It is thought he will not return again to the Court, before he hath eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed ſome good revenue for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of himſelf there. He is a Lord in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>differently well eſteemed of in the <hi>Roman</hi> Court, full of reſentment, very ſtirring, and will talk enough, eſpecially when the inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt of Kings is in queſtion; wherefore he is much favoured by their Miniſters. He alwaies keeps his promiſe, being never worſe then his word; he is very well ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compliſhed,
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:115287:48"/>and lacks nothing but the poſſibility of mony.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="26" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVI.</hi> Steffano Durazzo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>STeffano Durazzo,</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Genoua,</hi> of the new Nobility; he put himſelf in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Prelacie, and bought one after ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther both the Clerk of the Chambers, and the Apoſtolical General Treaſurors place, which he poſſeſſed but a little time, for that he was promoted by <hi>Urban</hi> to the Scarlet Gown. His holineſs imployed him in many Charges, and in particular, before the Warre, he ſent him Legate to the City of <hi>Ferrara;</hi> which Government he left, when as <hi>Antonio</hi> came thither to the aſſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance of the Army, and went to his Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick of <hi>Genoua,</hi> from whence he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver parted, but at ſuch time, as upon the vacancie of the Sea he repaired to the Conclave. He had a great deal of contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſie about the getting of that Arch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſhoprick, but it was <hi>Urbans</hi> pleaſure,
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:115287:49"/>that, in ſpight of his competitors, he ſhould enjoy it. In his Legateſhip of <hi>Ferrara</hi> he carried himſelf very wiſely, and to the ſatisfaction of thoſe people, as the Citizens themſelves ſay, but he was not much Courted by the Nobilitie. He is a rich Cardinal, becauſe he is a <hi>Genoueſe,</hi> whoſe Wealth doth multiply with Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chandiſing. Whilſt he was a Prelate he gamed away no ſmall ſummes of mony, and ſpent little leſs upon Women. He is purblind, and ſquints with one eye. In negotiating he is exceeding affable, but when the humor takes him, one muſt leave off negotiating with him. He ſeemes to be devoted to the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> but indeed is wholly <hi>French,</hi> and holds but little eſteem in the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="27" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:115287:49"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVII.</hi> Marc' Antonio Franciotti,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArc' Antonio Franciotti,</hi> a principal Gentleman of the Common-wealth of <hi>Lucca;</hi> he came to <hi>Rome,</hi> where putting himſelf into the Prelacie, he bought the Clerk of the Chambers place, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards that alſo of the Auditor thereof; but within a while he was by <hi>Urban</hi> promoted to the Scarlet Gown, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nored with many worthy Charges, and in particular was created Biſhop of <hi>Lucca,</hi> his Country. He was ſent Legate to <hi>Ravenna,</hi> and <hi>Romagna,</hi> where he was very well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded by that Nobilitie, and people. He grievouſly afflicted his Country, for the cauſe which I will here now deliver. The brother of this Cardinal, being one of the Miniſters in the Government of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, was diſcoverd to have plot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſome ſuch thing againſt his Country, as to have made himſelf Maſter of it; and in particular, there were found in his houſe a great many of Armes, not onely common, but alſo prohibited; and the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:115287:50"/>ſuſpition grew ſo much the greater, by how much they are in that City exceeding vigilant, and carefull, to ſee that no man enters armed into it, not ſo much as with a knife: Now the tranſgreſſors of this Law being alwaies rigorouſly puniſhed, the ſaid Cardinals brother was, together with his ſervants, committed to priſon, where being thoroughly examined and ſifted, the treaſon which they had contrived was made manifeſt in ſuch manner, as they purpoſed within a ſhort time to put them all to death. The Cardinal finding no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther way to repair the ruine of his Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, had recourſe unto Pope <hi>Urban,</hi> unto whom he recounted the matter, quite o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, then as indeed it was, ſaying, that his brother was made a priſoner, out of the hatred, and enmity, that the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles and Magiſtrates of <hi>Lucca</hi> bore unto him; and that they had charged him with rebellion, becauſe ſome of the ſervants of the Biſhops Palace were found Armed. Hereupon the Pope diſpatched away an expreſs poſt with letters, that comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded them to ſet the Delinquents at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty; but the Common-wealth refuſing to obey, his Holineſs, ſeeing their contumacy, interdicted, and excommunicated them;
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:115287:50"/>ſo that for a long time the exerciſe of the Divine Offices were not uſed, the Church dores remaining continually ſhut up. The Common-wealth publiſhed many pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtations, and writings, whereof they cauſed copies to be preſented to all Chriſtian Princes, but it nothing availed them; wherefore in the end they were conſtrained to yield unto the Popes pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and in this manner was the ſaid Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals brother, and all his complices ſet free. This Cardinal hath good abilities, is intelligent, and capable of the Papacie, but is not ripe enough for it. He is poor, and much affected to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> both he and all his Houſe living under the protection thereof. He is a wiſe man, and experimented in matters of the Court; he is well eſteemed of by the preſent Pope; in the ſacred Colledge he hath no Enemies of conſideration, and is friend enough to the <hi>Barberini:</hi> he may alſo with time break his Lance in <hi>Peters</hi> chair.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="28" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="90" facs="tcp:115287:51"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXVIII.</hi> Federico Carpegna.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FEderico Carpegna,</hi> a Noble man of the City of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbin:</hi> He was a poor Prelate; but <hi>Barberino</hi> having made uſe of him in ſome affairs of his, was ſo pleaſed with his carriage therein, that he took an affection to him, and at his inſtance he was by the Pope promoted to the Scarlet Gown, and therefore he is, and alwaies will be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and affected to them. The Count <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pegna,</hi> his brother, continually aſſiſted in the Warre of <hi>Urban</hi> againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi> This Cardinals endowments are mean, but he is able for buſineſs, and he may one day have ſome hope in the common pretenſions of the Scarlet Gownes, if the <hi>Barberini</hi> do not ſpoil his promotion, becauſe he is too much their ſervant. His vote will ever be, as that of the <hi>Barberini</hi> is, and therefore in time to come he will alwaies be <hi>French;</hi> beſides the affection he hath ſtill born to that Crown, although he makes no open profeſſion thereof. He is a man ſtudious, melancho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick, and ſomewhat charitable. He hath
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:115287:51"/>many brothers, whereof the Count is one, and another is a Canon of <hi>Santa Maria in Via lata.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="29" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXIX.</hi> Frenceſco Maria Brancaccio.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Maria Brancaccio,</hi> a <hi>Neopolitan</hi> Cavalier; he was Biſhop of the City of <hi>Capuccio</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples,</hi> where by reaſon of certain Eccleſiaſtical juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictions, he fell into ſome difference with a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Captain of foot, who was ſent unto that City by the Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples,</hi> and paſſing from words to blowes, he cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed him to be killed by a bardaſh of his with a muſket ſhot; for which <hi>Brancaccio</hi> was cited to appeare befor the Vice-Roy, to render an account of the man-ſlaughter committed by him. <hi>Brancaccio</hi> obeying, went to <hi>Naples;</hi> but the very ſame night he came thither, that he might not put him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf into the ſecular power of the Royall Court, he ſtole away in a felouque, and fled towards <hi>Rome;</hi> where being arrived, he imparted the whole matter unto <hi>Urban</hi>
                  <pb n="92" facs="tcp:115287:52"/>the eighth, who for the hate that he bore to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> not onely commended him for that he had done, but alſo defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded him. Which the Vice-Roy ſeeing, cauſed all his goods, and the revenues of his Biſhoprick to be ſequeſtred; ſo that this Prelate remained in <hi>Rome</hi> in ſuch ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſity and miſerie, as he could hardly make ſhift to live; but after that his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe was compiled, and that the Pope had abſolved him, he craved leave to return unto the reſidence of his Church, although the Kings Miniſters had expresſly forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den him ſo to doe, ſaying, that his Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique Majeſtie deſired of the Pope another Prelate for that City, &amp; had withall ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, that the inhabitants therof ſhould not permit him to enter into the poſſeſſion of it, upon pain of rebellion. It was the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune of this Lord, that whilſt he was lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Court, and departing to his reſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, the Pope was upon the point of pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moting Cardinals, with an intent to give the Hat unto my Lord <hi>Pier Luigi Caraffa,</hi> Biſhop of <hi>Tricario;</hi> and to my Lord <hi>Caraffa,</hi> Biſh, of <hi>Averſa,</hi> but both their promotions were hindred by the <hi>Colonneſi;</hi> the <hi>Barberini</hi> too preſt their Uncle to confer the Scarlet Gown on <hi>Serlupi</hi> their Couſin; but his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:115287:52"/>being moleſted and vext with theſe controverſies, would needs make the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verb good: <hi>Inter duos litigantes tertius gau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>det,</hi> and in ſtead of the reſt made <hi>Brancaccio</hi> Cardinal. Others ſay, that he promoted him to deſpight the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> by whom he was exceedingly hated, to the end that as a Prince of the holy Church he might be honored, and upon reſtoring of him to his Biſhoprick, he might alſo be reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced. A litle after his departure to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidence of his ſaid Church, and upon his arrival at <hi>Naples,</hi> he found two other Cardinals there, namely <hi>Aldobrandino,</hi> and <hi>Boncompagno;</hi> the one of them being come thither to have his part in the tiltings, hunting, and other feſtivals, which in that City were to be made for ſome victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries of <hi>Spain,</hi> and for the birth of a Son of the Kings; and the other was Archbiſhop of <hi>Naples. Brancaccio</hi> having continued there ſome monthes, the Count of <hi>Monte-Rei,</hi> at that time Vice-Roy of that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, preſented him with a paper from his Catholique Majeſtie, whereby he en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned him to depart with all ſpeed, not onely from <hi>Naples,</hi> but alſo quite out of the whole Kingdom; inſomuch that the poor Cardinal was forced to get him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:115287:53"/>in all haſt towards <hi>Rome,</hi> with all his family: Which <hi>Urban</hi> ſeeing, moved with indignation againſt the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and with compaſſion to the Cardinal, he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred the Biſhoprick of <hi>Viterbo</hi> on him, and giving him many Penſions, he not long after beſtowed on his Vicar the Biſhoprick of <hi>Aramo in Regno.</hi> This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal is much obliged to the <hi>Barberini;</hi> but in the Conclave, that he might not damni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie his kinſmen, he ſhewed himſelf affected to the Crown of <hi>Spain,</hi> and gave his vote to the <hi>Albernoz;</hi> with which ſtratagem, and to free himſelf from his obligation, he doth ſeek to draw unto him his kinſmen, and Nephewes, and accordingly hath already begun ſo to do, having maried one of them to one of the houſe of the <hi>Urſini.</hi> He is not well looked upon by <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, nor the <hi>Pamphilian</hi> family, for that he hath inconſiderately manifeſted him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf too much interreſſed in certain diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences about territories, between ſome of his Church, and others, the creatures of <hi>Donna Olimpia,</hi> in the City of <hi>Vitenbo.</hi> His Nephew, being Governor of <hi>Spoleti,</hi> was deprived thereof, and never ſince hath had any charge at all. To conclude, this Cardinal is poor, and proud.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="30" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="95" facs="tcp:115287:53"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXX.</hi> Rinaldo d'Eſte.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>RInaldo d'Eſte,</hi> a <hi>Modeneſe,</hi> and brother to the Duke of <hi>Modena:</hi> This Prince was promoted to the Scarlet Gown at the inſtance of the Emperour by <hi>Vrban</hi> the eighth; after which promotion the warre of <hi>Italy</hi> fell out between the Duke of <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma,</hi> and the <hi>Barberini;</hi> in regard whereof, though all differences were wholly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, yet hath he ſtill ſhewed himſelfe an enemy to the <hi>Barberini,</hi> and therefore in all the time that they raigned, he would ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver come to take the Hat, which after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he received from the hands of <hi>Inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent</hi> the tenth, being preſent in the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave at his election. Some moneths be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing paſt, the ſaid Cardinall tooke notice, that the <hi>Auſtrians</hi> made divers Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions about the intereſt of that Crown in the Pallace of <hi>Albernoz,</hi> whereunto his E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minencie was never called nor invited, as if they accompted him altogether indiffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent: now one day there was a conſiſtory to be held concerning the intereſt of <hi>Portu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gal,</hi> wherin ſome courſe was to be taken for
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:115287:54"/>the proviſion of thoſe Churches in the name of that King; and the Spaniſh Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters had by the Catholique Kings order forbidden all the Cardinalls of their facti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on from going to it: eſpecially the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall of <hi>Eſte</hi> was by the Duke of <hi>Savelli,</hi> the Emperours Embaſſadour, adviſed by no meanes to come at it; but he would not obey giving him this for an anſwer; That as the <hi>Spaniards</hi> had eſteemed his perſon of no conſideration in their Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſo his preſence would be of as little conſideration in the Conſiſtorie, &amp; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore he would goe unto it. Upon this oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion then he openly declared himſelfe diſtaſted with the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and he had a brieve granted to him for the protection of the Kingdome of <hi>France;</hi> whereupon this Cardinall of <hi>Eſte</hi> publiſhed a <hi>manifeſt,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the reaſons he had for his decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring himſelfe <hi>French,</hi> which was anſwered by the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and replyed unto by the Cardinall; who tooke downe the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Armes from his Pallace, and in the place thereof ſet up the moſt Chriſtian Kings. This <hi>Eſte</hi> began to defend the intereſt of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> becauſe they had offered him the Abbacie of <hi>Honantala,</hi> whereunto hee made ſome claime; wherefore the
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:115287:54"/>Pope ſaid one day unto him theſe words: My Lord, <hi>I ſee you labour much to protect the</hi> Barberini, <hi>and I doe not know the cauſe of ſuch a mutation, for you alwaies contraried them here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore, and now you ſtand for them; but I veri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y beleeve you doe it out of intereſt, for that they will reſigne unto you the Abbacie, whereunto you have ſo long pretended, or for ſome other end; howſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver know, that though it be in them to reſigne it, the paſſing of the Brieve thereof is in us. Eſte</hi> hearing this, thus anſwered; I doe not pretend, bleſſed Father, to defend the <hi>Barberini</hi> for any intereſt of mine, but to ſupplicate your Holineſs for juſt things: wherefore when as my abiding at court ſhall be diſpleaſing unto you, to give you ſatisfaction I will be gone. To this the Pope ſaid without any other reply, Bee you bleſſed; which in plaine termes is as much as to ſay, God be with you; and at the ſame inſtant the Cardinall getting in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Caroach with ſixe horſes went to <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prarola,</hi> and from thence to <hi>Modena</hi> his Country. Afterwards <hi>Eſte</hi> underſtanding that the Admirall of <hi>Caſtile</hi> was come to <hi>Rome</hi> as Embaſſador extraordinary from the Catholique King, to yeeld obedience to the Pope, and that he had declared hee would viſit all the Cardinalls, except him
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:115287:55"/>the ſaid <hi>Eſte,</hi> hee repaired againe to the Court; where, by reaſon of divers diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences that fell out between him and that Ambaſſador, they came to armes, and wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, what on the one ſide, and what on the other, above ſix hundred perſons; ſo that there was a great combuſtion in <hi>Rome,</hi> and ſome daily ſlaine, as is more amply delivered in a little printed relation there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: but the Pope raiſed men to ſuppreſſe this tumult, and ſo it was quieted by the meanes of certaine interpoſing Princes; but firſt this poore Lord, for the main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayning of his ſouldiers, was fain to pawne his jewells to the Cardinall <hi>Queva</hi> for the ſum of two and twenty thouſand crowns, by reaſon the mony which he expected from <hi>France</hi> came not time enough to him, and for that the Duke his brother could not ſupply him ſufficiently, in regard his ſtate was much exhauſted by the former warre with the <hi>Barberini.</hi> This Cardinall is bountifull enough, but his purſe failes him, and will not permit him to doe as he would do: he is of a good life, very con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſable, merry, and friendly.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="99" facs="tcp:115287:55"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> Franceſco Peretti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Peretti,</hi> alias Cardinall <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talto,</hi> he is the Nephewes Son of <hi>Sixtus quintus</hi> of happie memorie. This Lord was the onely ſonne of the Prince <hi>Perétti,</hi> who, being old, propoſed to give a wife to <hi>Franceſco,</hi> that was in love with a Lady of the Houſe of <hi>Ceſi,</hi> wherewith he acquain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted his father, who put him in good hope, and accordingly went, treated and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded the marriage, not for his Son, but for himſelfe, for the old dotard being in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitly taken with the Angelicall ſight of a moſt beautifull Lady, thought her more fitter for himſelfe, than for his ſonne. <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco,</hi> ſeeing he was in this ſort betrayed, and ill intreated by his Father, departed in a manner deſperate, and ſecretly, from the Court, and made himſelfe a Prieſt; by which meanes the father deceaſing not long after without heires, and all his States falling to <hi>Franceſco,</hi> upon his death the fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily of the <hi>Peretti</hi> will be extinct. This Lord uſed much diligence to get the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gowne, but could not attaine it, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:115287:56"/>
                  <hi>Urban</hi> was diſpleaſed with him, for that he would neither give, nor ſell unto him the delicious <hi>Villa</hi> of <hi>Mentana. Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talto</hi> would not give it unto him, leaſt the World ſhould ſay, that ſo deſerving a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon as himſelf attained to the Hat by bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berie; and ſo was contented rather to be without it. The moſt part of the States he poſſeſſeth, are ſcituated in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples;</hi> for which cauſe he is devoted to the Catholique Crown, and hath many times ſupplyed that Majeſtie with mony for the ſervice of his Warres. Hs is Prince of the City of <hi>Venafro,</hi> and Count of <hi>Celano,</hi> enjoying alſo many pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in the State of the Church: The King of <hi>Spain</hi> did oftentimes deſire the Scarlet Gown of Pope <hi>Urban</hi> for this Lord, but was by him continually refuſed; at length being earneſtly preſt by the King of <hi>France,</hi> who demanded it alſo for <hi>Giulio Mazzari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> the Pope, that he might not ſeem to be too much affected to the <hi>French,</hi> did at one and the ſame time promote both <hi>Mazzarino,</hi> and <hi>Montalto,</hi> as declared Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionals, and nominated by <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Spain.</hi> He is a rich Lord, and bountifull, keepes a Royal Court, and little cares what he ſpends, knowing well that after his deceaſe his eſtate is to fall unto divers
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:115287:56"/>Families, and in part cular to the <hi>Savelli,</hi> as his neereſt kinred. <hi>Sixtus quintus</hi> made a Bull, wherein he declared, that the Scarlet Gown ſhould be given to his deſcendants without any demand or inſtance at all; and indeed the <hi>Roman</hi> Church can ow no leſs to that blood of his, ſeeing it hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſo many benefits from that worthy high Biſhop of eternal memorie. All the Popes indevoured, but <hi>Sixtus quintus</hi> alone ſetled the Papal power, reduced unto o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience all the Barons, how great and potent ſoever they were, rooted the <hi>Ban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diti,</hi> and theeves out of the Eccleſiaſtical State, bridled the Chriſtian Princes, in a few years adorned <hi>Rome</hi> with ſumptuous fabricks, and inriched the <hi>Adrian Mole</hi> with a huge ſumme of Gold, intending to perform ſome great enterpriſe, which ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded not by reaſon of his enſuing death. This Cardinal holds good correſpondence with all the ſacred Colledge, except it be with the Cardinal <hi>Trivultio</hi> his kinſman; for there fell ought ſome difference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween them in the paſt Conclave, becauſe the ſaid <hi>Trivultio</hi> had heard, that <hi>Montalto</hi> was united with the <hi>French</hi> faction; but now, it is thought, they are reconciled. He is much eſteemed of by the Pope, is well conditioned, ſtudious, learned, and
<pb n="102" facs="tcp:115287:57"/>worthy of the Papacie for his goodneſs, and excellent qualities. He is of kinne to very near all the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobilitie, and was not long ſince honored by the Catholique King with the charge of conducting the Emperors Daughter, his new Spouſe, out of <hi>Germany</hi> into <hi>Spain;</hi> in which imployment the Cardinal ſtood not upon expence, but ſhewed himſelf exceeding ſplendid and liberal.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="32" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXII.</hi> Giulio Mazzarini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIulio Mazzarini,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Pier Mazzarini,</hi> a <hi>Sicilian,</hi> who being a Merchant, became bankrupt for certain ſummes of mony, and therefore fled with all his family to <hi>Rome,</hi> where the ſaid <hi>Giulio</hi> was born, as alſo his brother, named <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chael;</hi> who made himſelf a Frier of the Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minican Order. <hi>Giulio</hi> ſerved for ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time the <hi>Colonneſies</hi> Nephewes, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>Sachetti,</hi> who employed him in the managing of his monies; wherewith tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding for his Maſter, and with gaming,
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:115287:57"/>he got together no little ſummes for himſelf: Then he became a ſoldier; but returning again to the Court, he applied himſelf anew to the ſame Cardinals. The affection which <hi>Sachetti</hi> bore to this man, brought him into ſuch eſteem with the Cardinal <hi>Antonio,</hi> as he employed him in all his ſervices, and putting himſelf into the Prelacie, he was, at his inſtance, ſent by the Pope <hi>Nuncio</hi> Apoſtolical into <hi>Savoy,</hi> and alſo to take in his Holineſs name, out of the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> the City of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale,</hi> to be kept by him <hi>in depoſito,</hi> till ſuch time as the <hi>Spantards,</hi> and <hi>Germanes</hi> ſhould go out of, and leave the City of <hi>Mantoua,</hi> which they had ſeized upon, becauſe the Duke thereof had declared himſelf <hi>French,</hi> and would not acknowledge to hold of the Emperor. <hi>Mazzarini</hi> goes according<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and takes the City of <hi>Caſale in depo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito,</hi> but after he had cauſed the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and <hi>Germans</hi> to iſſue out of <hi>Mantoua,</hi> he gave <hi>Caſale</hi> again unto the <hi>French;</hi> by meanes whereof both the Emperor, and the King of <hi>Spain</hi> remain'd flouted, and cheated; and from this difference ſprung the bloody Warre in the State of <hi>Milan,</hi> and <hi>Monferrato.</hi> The ſaid <hi>Mazzarini,</hi> by this treaſon done unto the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> got
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:115287:58"/>the favour of the Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with that of the moſt Chriſtian King; who finding him to be a man of a wit pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for the deſignes of his Crown, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded the purple Gown of the Pope for him, in reward of the betraying the King of <hi>Spain</hi> his Lord, whoſe Vaſſal he is. <hi>Urban</hi> at that time denyed to give it him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he had alſo deceived him, in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigning the City of <hi>Caſale</hi> anew into the hands of the <hi>French,</hi> without his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge; and anſwered the moſt Chriſtian King, that he would grant it unto him for any other perſon that he would nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate: But his Majeſtie perſiſted ſtill with great obſtinacie in that his demand; which <hi>Urban</hi> ſeeing, could do no leſs then content him, and in this manner was he promotd to the Scarlet Gown. After the deceaſe of the Cardinal <hi>Richelieu,</hi> he had the whole Command; but his Maſters favor got him much hatred with the Grandees of the Kingdom. His Majeſtie greatly honored him; made him a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor of State, with authority to ſit in Parliament; and alſo at his death left him one of the Executors of his Teſtament. This Cardinal is grown ſo rich, that he is held to be the wealthieſt feuditary Prince that
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:115287:58"/>is. He had often craved leave of that King to return unto <hi>Rome,</hi> and take the Hat at ſuch time as <hi>Urban</hi> lived, but it would never be granted to him. He hath been ſo high in the Court of <hi>France,</hi> that the Princes of the blood could by no means endure it; which hath been the cauſe of ſuch revolutions in that King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and of ſuch inteſtine Wars as have followed thereupon; but this matter is ſo well known to every one, that I will paſſe from it, to diſcourſe of that, which further concernes him. This Cardinal is he, that, though a far off, did in the Conclave ſo oppoſe the election of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth; and not contented therewith, labored alſo to terrifie him, by ſending great armies in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to <hi>Italy;</hi> the operations whereof hath ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifeſted to the World, that the Cardinal had indeed other thoughts, then the ſole acquiſition of <hi>Piombino.</hi> The Catholique King hath declared him, and all his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Rebells and Traitors. At ſuch time, as this Cardinal ſerved in the Warres, he was a very vitious gamſter, and often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times received many hurts about women; but now he lives with much gravitie, and whoſoever hath to deal with him, finds him alwaies in apparance, gentle in
<pb n="106" facs="tcp:115287:59"/>ſpeech, and gratefull for benefits recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, wherefore he hath openly defended <hi>Barberino,</hi> ſo far forth, that he hath incur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the hatred of the Parliament of <hi>Paris</hi> for it. With his authority he cauſed his brother, being in a manner but a youth, to be elected General of the Order of the Dominicans, made him Maſter of the ſacred Palace, procured him the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Aix</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and finally not contented herewith, he ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained the Scarlet Gown for him; with all which honors the ſaid <hi>Michael</hi> is paſt into a better life.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="33" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIII.</hi> Marc' Antonio Bragadino.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MArc' Antonio Bragadino,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Venice:</hi> he was made Biſhop of the City of <hi>Vicenza,</hi> upon the nomination of the Republique, which knew him to be a good man, and of great integritie. This Biſhoprick of his enjoyes the tytle of Duke, Marqueſſe, and Count. All the time of his reſidence at his Church he was
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:115287:59"/>held in great eſteem, and lived with great reputation; I my ſelf have often ſeen him in that City, as he was going with his Clergy to the <hi>Domo,</hi> and me thought, that even then he ſhewed, and looked like a Cardinal, as within leſs then two years after he was made one, at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of the Signoria of <hi>Venice,</hi> which highly account of him. He is a Lord en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with many excellent qualities, is very courteous in ſalutes, and entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, loves not light converſations, is a man ſtudious, and curious; but his curio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie ceaſes, when matters of intereſt are handled. All the time, that he was at Court, he was never ſeen to give any alms, for which he was blamed; but it may well be, that he delights to give in ſecret, that he may not appear vain-glorious. This Cardinal cannot be Pope in haſt, for two reaſons; the one is, becauſe he is a <hi>Venetian,</hi> and the other is becauſe he is too young. He is not devoted to any Crown, but one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to his Republique, and his vote will be alwaies at the diſpoſing thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="31" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="108" facs="tcp:115287:60"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXI.</hi> Pietro Donato Ceſis.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PIetro Donato Ceſis,</hi> of a moſt Noble <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man</hi> Family; he was Clerk of the Chamber, was alſo made Treaſuror Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral of the holy Church, and afterwards promoted by <hi>Urban</hi> to the Scarlet Gown, and ſent by him Legate to <hi>Perugia,</hi> at ſuch time as the War was made againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy.</hi> The Apoſtoli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call Chamber, whilſt he had the admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of it, was well ſerved, and not op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed, as it had been by ſo many others, which robbed it. In this ſaid Legateſhip he caried himſelf very wiſely, but with rigor. He is a man of a good and ſincere life, and may be one day Pope, being a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man.</hi> He hath no hair on his Chin, ſo that he ſeems to be an Eunuch; and comming to be greyhaired, he would look like one of thoſe antient Popes; and not without cauſe was there a Paſquil made of him during the Vacancie of the Sea, which ſaid; <hi>Ceſis</hi> is made Pope, verily he will be a Pope <hi>de Malangonate.</hi> He would be no bad Pope, for that he is a lover of the poor,
<pb n="109" facs="tcp:115287:60"/>and a man of conſcience. He is learned, and naturally merry in converſation. He was Abbot of the Abbey of Saint <hi>Angelo à Sazanella</hi> in the Kingdom of <hi>Naples.</hi> He is much devoted to the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stria,</hi> and in particular to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique King, making open profeſſion thereof; and having his Majeſties armes ſet over his gate; and is loved and eſtee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med of that Crown, as alſo of the great Duke. He is not much reckoned of in the Court, but is reverenced in the ſacred Colledge. He hath no enemies, except it be the <hi>Barberini,</hi> who fear him for the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes they have done to the Duke of <hi>Ceſis,</hi> beſides other diſguſts received in his own perſon from them. There hath ſome diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taſt alſo paſt between him and the Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Theodoli,</hi> in a Chappel held by the Cardinals for the love of <hi>Lerida.</hi> His Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment would be good for the holy Church; for ſome of his confidents have reported, that if ever he ſhould attain to that degree, he would with all his intereſt make a league againſt the <hi>Turke;</hi> and would alſo, if God gave himliſe, lay up as many millions of Gold in the Caſtle, as <hi>Sixtus quintus</hi> did, for the benefit of the Apoſtolick Sea. His kindred are the <hi>Orſini,</hi>
                  <pb n="110" facs="tcp:115287:61"/>the Duke <hi>Acquaſparta,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Ceſis,</hi> the <hi>Soovelli,</hi> and others.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="35" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXV.</hi> Franceſco Maria Machiavelli,</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FFranceſco Maria Machiavelli,</hi> a Noble man of <hi>Florence,</hi> and Couſin to the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berini.</hi> He was a firſt but a ſimple Prelate, then was made Biſhop of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards promoted to the Scarlet Gowne for divers reaſons, but the moſt intimate of them was, becauſe he was a kinne to the <hi>Barberini</hi> by the mothers ſide; another was, for that the Cavalier <hi>Matthia Machi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avelli,</hi> who was Captain of the light-horſe of his Holineſſe guard, and had done ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſervices for the Pope in the paſt Warre againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> was an earneſt ſuitor to him for it. This Cardinal is very affable in his demeanor, of a good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, curteous, and a friend to the poor, but yet ſpends not much upon them of his own purſe. He is not diſliked of by the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> though he be the <hi>Barberinies</hi> Couſin, becauſe he hath never
<pb n="111" facs="tcp:115287:61"/>diſtaſted that Prince, but hath held good correſpondence with him by all manner of ſervices, if not openly, at leaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſecretly, for otherwiſe he had loſt the Popes favor. He is neither <hi>Spaniſh</hi> nor <hi>French,</hi> feigning himſelf neutral, but in ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect is wholly <hi>Auſtrian;</hi> and in the paſt Conclave he alwaies ſided with <hi>Albernoz</hi> againſt <hi>Franceſco.</hi> He was not diſpleaſed to ſee the <hi>Barberini</hi> perſecuted by the Pope, knowing their miſdeanors deſerved that, and worſe. He is well regarded by his ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſſe, and is now reſident at his Church of <hi>Ferara.</hi> He is a man of an indifferent un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, hath no conſiderable enemies, nor any contrarietie, but ſuch as he may have by reaſon of his affinitie with the <hi>Barberini:</hi> he is of a goodly preſence, and young; he maintaines himſelf in his Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oprick with much decorum and gravitie, carrying himſelf with the great ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the people there, by whom he is lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, reverenced and ſerved.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="36" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="112" facs="tcp:115287:62"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVI.</hi> Verginio Orſini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Verginio Orſini,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> Nephew to the Duke of <hi>Bracciano,</hi> and the bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of the Duke of <hi>Santo Gemini;</hi> he was onely an Abbot, and thought to have caſt off his Clerical habit, and have maried the Princeſs <hi>Lodoviſia:</hi> but <hi>Urban,</hi> envying this match, and whilſt it was a making up, promoted him in a Conſiſtory to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown. Others ſay, that the Duke of <hi>Bracciano,</hi> finding his houſe without the red Hat, courted the Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> a long time with donatives, and exorbitant expences; and in the end, with a great ſumme of Gold drew him to get his Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to promote him: howſoever the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown was due to him, as a deſerving Lord, and of a moſt antient family, which, as one may ſay, hath had as many Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals as daies; and the <hi>Roman</hi> Church is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedingly obliged to this houſe, their an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſtors having fought for it, and kept the <hi>Barbarians</hi> far enough from <hi>Rome;</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining the Apoſtolical Sea in all ſecuri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie. This Houſe, as alſo that of the <hi>Colonne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſi</hi>
                  <pb n="113" facs="tcp:115287:62"/>alone, have a place with the Ambaſſadors in the Chappel, but in regard of preceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie they never meet there both together. This Cardinal according to his authority is not very rich; no more than his anceſtors were, who warred a long time with the <hi>Colonneſi,</hi> in ſuch ſort as they put not only the neighbouring Princes in fear, but alſo the very Popes themſelves, who were fain to obſerve them; but they have now reduced them to that paſſe, as the <hi>Orſini</hi> may with juſt reaſon ſay, <hi>ſaſtiditum in ques, &amp; opprebrium gentibus, &amp; abjectio plebis;</hi> howſoever this Lord is bountiful, as farre forth as his ſmall abilitie will extend, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying along with him the liberalitie of his race. He was much beloved and regarded of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, becauſe at ſuch time as the aſſuming of Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio</hi> to the Papacie was in agitation, he being not entred into the Conclave, by reaſon of ſome indiſpoſition of his, when there was need of his vote, he preſently entred, and gave it for him; the ſaid <hi>Orſini</hi> too were great furtherers of the match between his holineſſe Neece and the Prince <hi>Lodoviſio:</hi> Nevertheleſs at this preſent, the <hi>French</hi> ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving deprived the Prince <hi>Lodoviſio</hi> of the Principalitie of <hi>Piombino,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Orſini</hi>
                  <pb n="114" facs="tcp:115287:63"/>indeavour all that ever they may to ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain it, for that the Duke of <hi>Braccianoes</hi> Wife is of the <hi>Appian</hi> houſe, from whom the <hi>Spaniards</hi> formerly took away the ſaid Principalitie, and ſold it to the Prince <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doviſio</hi> for the ſum of five hundred thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes, being worth threeſcore thouſand a year. The <hi>Orſini</hi> were hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore devoted to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> but now have declared themſelves <hi>French,</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſomuch that the Duke of <hi>Bracciano</hi> and the Cardinal have ſet up the Armes of the moſt Chriſtian King, from whom they have a Penſion of two and twenty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand Crownes a year; beſides the Duke of <hi>Bracciano</hi> continually expects the Brieve of the. Inveſtiture of <hi>Piombino:</hi> For which cauſe it is believed, that the friendſhip and familiaritie, which hath been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth and them, will turn into hatred and difference, and all-ready there is a beginning thereof; for his holineſs hath cauſed the Duke of <hi>Bracciano</hi> to be cited, to make payment of his debts to the <hi>Montiſti</hi> his Creditors, otherwiſe threatning to make ſale of his goods to ſatisfie them. This Cardinal is a man proud enough, and for matter of prece<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, he, by making ſtay of his Caroach,
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:115287:63"/>affronted &amp; ill intreated the family of the Reſident of the deceaſed Queen Mother, <hi>Maria de Medici.</hi> He is a Lord full of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentment, and Vindicative, and therefore is feared in the Court, and reverenced in the Colledge.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="37" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVII.</hi> Giulio Gabrielli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIulio Gabrielli,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Nobleman: he was Clerk of the Chamber, and was promoted to the Scarlet Gown by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, for the making of mony by ſale of that Office; and afterwards was ſent, as it were in exile, unto a miſerable Biſhoprick, charged with penſions, in the City of <hi>Aſcoli;</hi> the greateſt part of his meanes he acknowledgeth from the houſe of <hi>Lancelloti.</hi> He hath received many diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſts from <hi>Barberino,</hi> yet can he not for all that ſeparate himſelf from him. He ſeemes to be devoted to the houſe of <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtria,</hi> but is internally <hi>French.</hi> He is an in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent man, ſtudious, curious, and affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble in his dealing. He is a poor Cardinal,
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:115287:64"/>and therefore give not much almes. He is but young, in regard whereof nothing is to be ſaid of him concerning the Papacie. He is well qualified, leades a retired life, hath no enemies in the ſacred Colledge, and in the Court carries a good port; he hath ſome Nephewes, which are of no ill condition. He is a kinne to divers Noble <hi>Roman</hi> Families, and in particular to the <hi>Altieri, Lancelloti,</hi> and <hi>Coccini.</hi> This Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal hath in his Biſhoprick been at ſome variance with the people thereof, inſomuch that they roſe up tumultuouſly againſt him, about ſome taxes impoſed by him upon them.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="38" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="117" facs="tcp:115287:64"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXVIII.</hi> Aſcanio Filomarini.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>AScanio Filomarini,</hi> a <hi>Neapolitan</hi> Cavali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, born in a little Village ſubject to <hi>Benevento,</hi> called <hi>Chianchiſella:</hi> He was ſo poor, that to repair the miſerie he was in, he reſolved to goe, and ſerve ſome Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in the Court of <hi>Rome;</hi> where being ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived, he addreſſed himſelf to a Cardinal, his Countriman, and friend, to the end that with his authoritie he might be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferred to the place of Maſter of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, to ſome perſon that was capable of the Papacie; but he to gull him, rather then otherwiſe, recommended him to <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berino,</hi> that was not in a predicament of being Pope, who entertained him for Maſter of his Chamber; and it was his for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tune to have the ſame inclination, that his Lord had; both of them delighted in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrologie; for which cauſe <hi>Maffeo</hi> carried the greater affection unto him. In proceſſe of time <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth hapned to die, and after long conteſtation in the Conclave amongſt the Cardinals of ſeveral <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> factions they elected the ſaid <hi>Maffeo Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berino</hi>
                  <pb n="118" facs="tcp:115287:65"/>for Pope, by the name of <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth; who after he had promoted <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco Barberino</hi> his Nephew, to the Scarlet Gown, appointed the ſaid <hi>Fidoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini</hi> to be his ſuperintendant, with the Title of Maſter of his Chamber, and au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thoritie to wear purple; in regard <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco</hi> was by reaſon of his youth too unapt, and not fit for the Government. <hi>Barberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no,</hi> ſome time being paſt, not able longer to endure to ſee himſelf under the charge of the Maſter of his Chamber, began to withdraw himſelf from it with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt arrogancie, that might be; and had in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed driven him out of his Court, had it not been for the Pope, his Uncle, who protected him: howſoever he would not make uſe of him in any thing, but about the Chamber. <hi>Filomarini,</hi> having ſerved the Popes houſe for the ſpace of ten years, reſolved to trie his fortune, to ſee if he could get the Scarlet Gown, becauſe it had been often promiſed to him by his holineſſe, but it little availed him; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when he ſaw that the Pope had made many promotions, and that he was ſtill ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, he began to fall from the hope, which continually he had of it. The truth is, that <hi>Urban</hi> had an intent to promote
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:115287:65"/>him; but he was by <hi>Franceſco</hi> with a malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous policie kept from it; for he would ſay to his holineſs, Father, <hi>Filomarini</hi> is to me a right hand for the Government of my af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs, and I ſhall not be able to meet with ſuch another, as he is; wherefore you may be pleaſed to preferre him ſome other time; and this he did alwaies at ſuch time, as the promotions were to be made, more for the hate that he bore him, then for a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other end, hoping that by meanes of this ſuſpenſion, his Uncle comming to die, he ſhould not ſee a ſervant of his exalted to the ſame Dignitie that he was in. The Arch-biſhoprick of <hi>Naples</hi> becomming void by the death of the Cardinal <hi>Buon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compagno, Filomarini,</hi> ſeeing that four and twenty years were already paſt, and he had not been remunerated with any thing, determined to craveit for a reward of his labors, as indeed he did, ſaying, <hi>Bleſſed Father, I have long ſerved your Holineſſe, and your Houſe, and never had any occaſion to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand any grace of you, till now, that the Church of</hi> Naples <hi>is void, which I humbly beſeech your Holineſſe to beſtow on me;</hi> And this he ſpake even with tears in his eyes, becauſe he had loſt all hope of the Scarlet Gown: the Pope, to make himſelf merry with him,
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:115287:66"/>anſwered him thus; <hi>This is not a morſell for you, my</hi> Aſcanio, <hi>but for a Cardinal; and wee have already ſo deſtinaled it:</hi> Which <hi>Filoma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini</hi> hearing, made no reply, but ſhrinking up his ſhoulders took his leave. Not long after this <hi>Urban</hi> communicated unto <hi>Fran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſco</hi> the promotion of the Cardinals, which he meant to make, and in particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of <hi>Filomarini;</hi> but <hi>Franceſco,</hi> having uſed all the perſwaſions he might to divert him from it, and not prevailing, reſolved to give him all the diſguſts in the mean time, that poſſibly he could; and for a begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, one day when <hi>Barberino</hi> was going forth into the City, <hi>Filomarini</hi> brought his cloak, as he was wont, to put it on him; but <hi>Franceſco</hi> in a rage ſnatched it out of his hand, ſaying, you ſhall ſerve me no longer, and turning him about to another Gentleman of his there preſent, he gave it to him, and ſaid, <hi>you ſhall ſerve me hereafter for the Maſter of my Chamber:</hi> which <hi>Filomarini</hi> ſeeing and hearing, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained as one dead, to find himſelf ſo diſgraced by his Lord, ſaying in his mind; <hi>Is this my Guerdon for ſo many yeares ſervice, which I have done to the Pope, and his Nephews? curſed be he which truſteth in the deceitful hopes of the World.</hi> Now the monday morning
<pb n="121" facs="tcp:115287:66"/>came, appointed for the ſitting of the Conſiſtory, where preparation being made for things neceſſary thereunto, <hi>Filo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marini</hi> alſo began to go about, as he uſed to doe at other times; but <hi>Barberino</hi> with bitter words commanded him to get him from that place: as he did, retiring to his lodging very melancholick, and excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly caſt down. The time of the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtory being come, which laſted ſix whole hours together, his holineſſe in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning propounded the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Naples</hi> for <hi>Filomarim,</hi> and afterward toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with many others, promoted him to the Scarlet Gown. The Conſiſtory being finiſhed, there was heard, according to the uſual cuſtome, crying out, long live Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal ſuch a one: <hi>Filomarini,</hi> who knew nothing of that which had paſt, deſirous to hear ſomewhat, went out of his lodging, and preſently met with ſome Prelates and Cardinals, which did all reverence unto him, ſaying, <hi>your Eminencies ſervant, my Lord Cardinal</hi> Aſcanio; he thinking he was mocked, anſwered each of them, <hi>I had as lieve be flouted by you as another:</hi> but at length <hi>Barberino</hi> himſelf was forced to goe to him, and give him the Title of Eminencie: <hi>Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lomarini</hi> hearing what he, and the reſt had
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:115287:67"/>ſaid unto him, began to come to himſelf again, and call to mind the Popes words, when he told him, that it was not a morſel for him, and that he had deſtinated it to a Cardinal. This Lord got the Hat with the ſweat of four and twenty years ſervice; and in the laſt Conclave, he met ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently with <hi>Barberino,</hi> when as he told him, that his obligation for the Scarlet Gown was due to the good memory of <hi>Urban,</hi> and that he being dead, his obligation was alſo extinct, knowing well, that he had al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies oppoſed him in his attaining to the Hat, and that therefore he was obli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged to give his vote for the Catholick King his Lord. <hi>Urban</hi> tooke the greater affection to this Cardinal, becauſe when he was grievouſly ſick in his laſt infirmity, he had demanded of his Phyſitian in what ſtate of health his holineſſe was, and being put in good hope thereof by him, he gave him a chain of Gold, which the Phyſitian ſhewed to the Pope; who there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by perceiving the love he bore to him, promoted him afterwards to the Scarlet Gown. In the time of the Warre of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> he ſent twelve thouſand Piaſtre to the relief of the Papal Army, for which he got no litle credit with the
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:115287:67"/>Pope, and ſacred Colledge. He is a very intelligent man, and given to Aſtrolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, but is exceeding proud; ſo that in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard thereof, there is no Cavalier how mean ſoever, that Courts and viſits him: And I well remember, that the Counteſſe of <hi>Saponara</hi> at ſuch time as he was Maſter of the Chamber to <hi>Barberino,</hi> ſent him certain letters, ſuperſcribed with the Title of my Lord, and becauſe they had not the Title of moſt illuſtrious, he returned them back, ſaying, that they were not ſent unto him; and as much he did, when as he was illuſtrious, ſaying, that they were not directed to him: in ſumme, no man knowes, how to negotiate with him, and therefore every one abſtaines from writing unto him.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="39" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="124" facs="tcp:115287:68"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XXXIX.</hi> Gieronimo Veroſpi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIeronimo Veroſpi,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Gentleman; He was Auditor <hi>della Rota,</hi> as in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner his Uncle had been, who during the time of his being ſo, faling at odds with the great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> madly undertook w<hi rend="sup">th</hi> certain Muſketiers to diſpute the diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence that was between them about ſome waters, without regarding the danger of his life, that hung over his head; after which returning to <hi>Rome,</hi> he was by <hi>Urban</hi> thought worthy of the Scarlet Gown; and having obtained it, he lived but a while, for ſome diſguſts that were given him broke his heart, and ſo he dyed. <hi>Urban,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the death of that Cardinal, ſeeing his houſe as it were ruined &amp; undone, and bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a great affection to it, promoted the preſent <hi>Geronimo Veroſpi</hi> his Nephew to the Hat; he conferred alſo upon him the Church of <hi>Oſimo nella Marca,</hi> and further confirmed the Auditors place <hi>della Rota</hi> on his brother, beſides many other benefits and graces. <hi>Franceſco</hi> and <hi>Antonio</hi> both made great ſuite to have the Scarlet
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:115287:68"/>Gown as well for <hi>Verospi</hi> as for <hi>Gabrieli,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they were but ſmall friends to <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> and as ſuch, they ſhewed themſelves obſtinate againſt his election; and therefore after his aſſumption the ſaid <hi>Verospi</hi> hath alwaies abſented himſelf from the Court, to avoid thoſe diſguſts which might happen unto him, reſiding continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally at his Biſhoprick. He is a poor Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, and hath many brothers, who all live together with their Mother, except it be one which hath ever kept himſelf apart from the reſt; and after the death of <hi>Urban</hi> he went to ſerve Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> in the place of Maſter of his Chamber, before he left the Court of <hi>Rome</hi> to go into <hi>France.</hi> This Cardinal is learned, but the Auditor <hi>della Rota</hi> his brother is more intelligent; his vote will be altogether for the <hi>Barberi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ni,</hi> and his inclination is more to <hi>France</hi> then to <hi>Spain,</hi> although, to maintain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf in the common pretenſions, he ſeemes in apparance to be neutral. If this ſame Lord ſhould be Pope, he would ſpoil the ſeat of <hi>Peter</hi> to accommodate his brethe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, which are many.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="40" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="126" facs="tcp:115287:69"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XL.</hi> Gaſpare Matthei.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GAspare Matthei,</hi> brother to the Duke of that ſurname; He was a Prelate of a moſt Noble and antient <hi>Roman</hi> family; and was ſent by <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the eighth Nuneio to the Emperors Majeſtie; in which Charge he carried himſelf with much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of both parts. He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown, as other <hi>Nuncioes</hi> were: Upon his return to <hi>Rome</hi> he was preſently ſet upon by <hi>Sachetti</hi> for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>payment of ſix thouſand crownes, lent him at his going into <hi>Germany,</hi> cauſing him to be cited for it, in regard whereof he is no great friend to him, but greatly oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed his fortune in the Conclave, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haved himſelf with much vigilancie, care, &amp; affection towards the Houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> in favor of the Cardinal <hi>Phamphilio:</hi> And he it was alſo that made a great coil, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, they would have no forreign, but <hi>Roman</hi> Popes; and in the ſame Conclave he defended the reputation of the houſe of <hi>Austria,</hi> threatning the Cardinal
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:115287:69"/>
                  <hi>Rapacioli,</hi> who had ſpoken amiſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Auſtrians;</hi> he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf alſo averſe to the Cardinal <hi>Fiorenzola</hi> for the ſame cauſe. This Cardinal is poor, intelligent, opinnative, haughty, proud, full of reſentment, and lookes more like a ſouldier then a Cardinal: He ſpeakes freely againſt any one whatſoever he be, when he ſees things ill done, His vote is, and ever will be <hi>Auſtrian,</hi> and for that Crown would he ſhed his owne blood. He is well eſteemed of by the Pope, and feared of the Court, as a vindicative per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. He hath allied himſelf with the houſe of <hi>Gonzaga,</hi> having given his Siſter in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riage to the Prince of <hi>Pozzolo,</hi> who was heretofore Ambaſſador in this Court from the Emperor.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="41" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLI.</hi> Girolamo Grimaldi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIrolamo Grimaldi,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noua,</hi> and kinſman to the Prince of
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:115287:70"/>
                  <hi>Montehonorato.</hi> This <hi>Girolamo</hi> was a ſoldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, having ſerved the Emperor in the Warres of <hi>Germany;</hi> returning into his Country he put on the long robe, and comming to <hi>Rome,</hi> he bought the Clerk of the Chambers place, was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth made Governor of <hi>Rome,</hi> in which Charge he carried himſelf with much ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction of the people; at the end where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of he was ſent <hi>Nuntio</hi> into <hi>France,</hi> and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving remained ſome monthes in that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment, he was promoted to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown for two reſpects; the one was to make the Clerke of the Chambers place void for the ſelling of it; and the other, to ſhew the promoting of a <hi>French Nuntio.</hi> Some ſay that this Lord was he which cauſed the Prince of <hi>Monaco</hi> to fall from the <hi>Spaniards;</hi> but others more certainly ſay, that it was a <hi>French</hi> Cavalier, named Mounſieur <hi>Bordon,</hi> of the ſelf ſame Houſe of <hi>Grimaldi;</hi> for there are in <hi>France</hi> many of that Family, ſo that it cannot be deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed but that the Cardinal had an hand in it. And the cauſe of this defection was, for that the Kings Miniſters would not pay the Garriſon which was kept in the fortreſs of <hi>Monaco;</hi> in regard whereof the poor Prince, having no poſſibility to pay
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:115287:70"/>them, by reaſon he was not ſatisfied thoſe few aſſignments which had been ſetled for it, was forced to expel the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and introduce the <hi>French,</hi> as moſt profi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table for him, reſtoring to the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique King his Golden Fleece again. This Cardinal is well accommodated with the goods of fortune, and yet he cannot be ſaid to be rich, if one conſider the bountifull<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of his mind, which is ſuch, as his meanes, though ſufficient enough, is not able to anſwer. In his negotiating and dealings he is very affable and courteous, honoring all without exception of any. He lives under the protection of the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> as all his kinred beſides doth. He is intelligent enough, and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but much more curious. The moſt Chriſtian King honored him for ſome monthes with his comprotection of <hi>France,</hi> in default of <hi>Antonioes</hi> abſence from the Court, it having been exerciſed before by Cardinal <hi>Brichi;</hi> and now it is exerci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by the Cardinal of <hi>Eſte,</hi> with the Title of Legitimate Protector, for which he hath received a Brieve from his Majeſtie. <hi>Grimaldi</hi> got but little favor with the Pope in the time that he exerciſed the ſaid comprotection, having too openly
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:115287:71"/>ſpoken overmuch in the behalfe of the <hi>Barberini;</hi> in regard whereof his Holineſſe, before the Cardinal of <hi>Eſtes</hi> arrival at <hi>Rome,</hi> oftentimes denyed him audience. He is very open in the expreſſion of his ſence, eſpecially when he comes to have a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny buſineſſe impoſed upon him. He is of ſome account in the Court, becauſe he is of a principal Family, and a Nobleman of the City of <hi>Genoua.</hi> He is not a little glad at any loſſe, or miſadventure hapning to the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> Monarchy, and in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular to that of <hi>Spain.</hi> He is an amiable Lord, merry, and jovial; is well pleaſed with the delights of the World, and eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially with faire Women. He is much eſteemed of by the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="42" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="131" facs="tcp:115287:71"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLII.</hi> Ceſare Fachinetti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CEſare Fachinetti,</hi> Nephew to <hi>Innocent</hi> the ninth, and a Nobleman of <hi>Bologna;</hi> he was a deſerving Prelate, and ſent <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cio</hi> to the Catholique King; at the end of which imployment he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, and afterwards had conferred on him the Biſhoprick of <hi>Sinigaglia,</hi> a City of the State of <hi>Urbin.</hi> In his Church he was obſerved to be a good and vigilant man, behaving himſelf gently and charitably towards his flock. None of the Cardinals in the ſacred Colledge are enemies to him, becauſe he is loving to them all. He is not very old, but comming to ſome riper age he may attain to <hi>Peters</hi> Chair; the rather for that he is devoted to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria;</hi> he hath no vices of conſideration; holds good correſpondence with the Popes Family. The <hi>Spaniards</hi> would condiſcend to his election, ſo that it might be propounded by ſome head of a faction; for if they ſhould do it themſelves, he might be eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly excluded. He would be no bad Pope
<pb n="132" facs="tcp:115287:72"/>for the good of the Church. <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth hath conferred on his brother the Charge of Governor of the Armes in <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magna;</hi> who in caſe of his being Pope, would be he that will reign, and hath no conſiderable defect, ſaving that he is ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what amorous, being now in love with one <hi>Nina Barcarola,</hi> a famous <hi>Roman</hi> Dame, otherwaies they are both good Cavaliers. The vote of this Cardinal will be alwaies for <hi>Spain.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="43" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIII.</hi> Franceſco Rapaccioli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Rapaccioli,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> deſcended from a Caſtle, called <hi>Caſtel di Scepoli,</hi> ſcituated betwixt the City of <hi>Narni</hi> and <hi>Trani,</hi> and was the Sonne of a <hi>Lilettaro,</hi> for ſo they call thoſe in <hi>Rome</hi> which ſell Shirts, Smocks, Handkerchers, and other kind of linnen in the City. Being a Prelate, he was Clerk of the Chamber, and by <hi>Urban</hi> was againſt the will of the whole Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge made Treaſuror General of the holy Church; having been firſt honored with
<pb n="133" facs="tcp:115287:72"/>the charge of Commiſſary General of the Papal Army in <hi>Perugia:</hi> After ſometime he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown, to make mony of the Clerks place for the uſe of the Warre, and a leſſe while did he enjoy and exerciſe the Treaſuror<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, being daily and continually imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the ſaid Warre. He is a rich Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal according to his qualitie, and is moſt intelligent in the Civil and Cannon Lawes. He is of the <hi>Barberinies</hi> faction, and conſequently <hi>French;</hi> wherefore in the Conclave he ſpake amiſſe of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> for which <hi>Matthei</hi> anſwered him as he deſerved, and with threats told him, that he were beſt take heede in what manner he ſpake of the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> for elſe he might be made to repent it, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were a Cardinal. He is but litle eſteemed of in the Court, and in the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Colledge he is reputed as a meer Scarlet Gown, and no otherwiſe. <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth hath conferred on him the Church of <hi>Terni</hi> his Country.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="44" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="134" facs="tcp:115287:73"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIIII.</hi> Giovannni Giacomo Panzirolo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIovanni Giacomo Panzirolo,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> the Sonne of <hi>Virgilio della valle,</hi> ſo ſirna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, ſometime a publique Taylor in <hi>Rome. Giovanni Giacomo,</hi> having profited well in vertue, and proceeded Doctor in the Lawes, applied himſelf to the Court, where he was entertained by the now Pope for his Auditor, at ſuch time as he was a Prelate, and Nuntio at <hi>Naples;</hi> He alſo followed the ſaid <hi>Pamphilio</hi> into <hi>Spain,</hi> upon his going likewiſe Nuntio thither. After <hi>Pamphilio</hi> was promoted to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown, <hi>Panzirolo</hi> put himſelf into the Prelacie, and having exerciſed many Charges and Governments, he was at laſt ſent Nuntio into <hi>Spain,</hi> where he caried himſelf very worthyly, and to the great contentment of that Majeſtie; inſomuch that the Pope finding him to be very in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent, and deſerving, promoted him to the Scarlet Gown. He is a learned man, and expert in all matters of Negotiation: He hath gotten much credit with the Crown of <hi>Spain;</hi> is greatly approved of in
<pb n="135" facs="tcp:115287:73"/>the Court, and is much eſteemed by the ſacred Colledg, but farre more by <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, ſo that if he live, he may be Pope. He is of a ſweet coverſation, excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently qualified, of a good behaviour, friendly, and thankful for all benefits re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived. He arrived at <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Spain</hi> when as the Cardinals were in a manner all ſhut up in the Conclave, and brought along with him divers pacquets of letters written from his Catholique Majeſtie, to all the ſacred Colledge, in favor of the Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> inſomuch that it was he who gave the firſt ſtart to his greatneſs; which benefit, together with the good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>will <hi>Pamphilio</hi> bore him before, cauſed him preſently upon his aſſumption to place him near about him; he gave him lodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings alſo in the Pontifical Palace, and made him his chief Counſellor of State; ſo that the whole Government of the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pacie is in a manner reſting upon his ſhoulders. He is not very rich, but with the Penſions and Benefices beſtowed on him by the Pope, he is thought to be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding well accommodatep. He leades a very retired life, and is of a good diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; for I remember that in the time of his Prelacie he told me one day, how he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:115287:74"/>fell out with, nor miſuſed any ſervant of his houſe, to the end they ſhould not have occaſion to murmure at him, or his birth, and loſe the reſpect which they owed unto him; a matter verily worthy of commendation. He is a truſty friend of the great Duke of <hi>Toſcans,</hi> but he is not confided in by the <hi>Barberini</hi> for private intereſts, and becauſe, as it is thought, he was one of them that Counſelled the Pope to proſecute them in that ſort, as he did; He received the Hat from the hands of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, together with the Cardinal of <hi>Eſte,</hi> becauſe they were not preſent in the Court at ſuch time as <hi>Urban</hi> was living.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="45" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLV.</hi> Mattheo Theodoli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>MAttheo Theodoli,</hi> a <hi>Roman,</hi> deſcended of a Noble family in the City of <hi>For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin Popoli nella Romagna.</hi> He was a poor Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late that could hardly live, but at the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of <hi>Antonio</hi> he was by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth made Auditor of the Chamber,
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:115287:74"/>and not having mony enough to pay for it, the ſaid Cardinal <hi>Antonio</hi> lenthim ſome, out of the affection he bore to his houſe: He exerciſed the ſaid Auditorſhip but a ſhort while, ſo that he could hardly recover a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny part of his disburſment, becauſe he was promoted to the Scarlet Gown out of a neceſſity of ſelling that Office to make mony of, for the ſupplying of the Warre againſt the Princes of <hi>Italy;</hi> by which meanes he became exceeding poor, and therefore he reſolved to abandon the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh,</hi> and betake himſelf to the <hi>French</hi> par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, upon promiſe from that Crown of mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny and penſions. This Cardinal is of little eſteem in the ſacred Colledge, inſomuch that when he meant to give himſelf to the <hi>French,</hi> he ſent a Gentleman of his to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe him to Cardinal <hi>Montalto,</hi> ſaying, that his Eminencie was to pardon him for leaving the <hi>Auſtrian,</hi> and cleaving to the <hi>French</hi> devotion, in regard he was redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced thereunto by meer neceſſitie; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto the ſaid <hi>Montalto</hi> made anſwer, that his Catholique Majeſtie in loſing him loſt nothing, and the King of <hi>France</hi> by geting him got litle. Not long after inſued the Conclave, where, it is ſaid, he carried himſelf with little fidelity to the moſt
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:115287:75"/>Chriſtian King; for being promiſed I know not what ſumme of mony, together with the Biſhoprick of <hi>Imola,</hi> he falſifyed the Marqueſs of <hi>Sanſciamont</hi> the Ambaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor of <hi>France</hi> his hand to certain letters, in the behalf of the Cardinal <hi>Pamphilio,</hi> for which he was turned out of his Majeſties favor, and likewiſe deprived of all the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefits and revenues which he enjoyed in that Kingdom; whereupon, not being able to live as a Cardinal, he, very much dejected, abſented himſelf from the Court and went to the Marqueſſe <hi>ſanto Vito</hi> his brother; where out of rage and diſcontent he became almoſt frantick, and the Pope having granted him the Church of <hi>Imola,</hi> took it away again from him, and confer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red it on my Lord <hi>Cocino Romano,</hi> who was Biſhop of <hi>Turſi.</hi> After he had remained ſome time with his ſaid brother, he retur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Court, where unknown he li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved miſerably: but at length having re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived ſome letters from <hi>France,</hi> it is ſaid that he ſpake thus publiquely to the Pope; <hi>Bleſſed Father, the moſt Chriſtian King hath vouochſaſed to receive me a new into his priſtine favor, as much as to ſay, in de spight of all my il willers, and of ſuch as would not have it ſo.</hi> There can no certaine judgement be
<pb n="139" facs="tcp:115287:75"/>made what this Cardinals vote will be, for he turnes like a leafe with every breath of winde. Both the King of <hi>France,</hi> and the Pope make but little account of him, and yet they ſeem to look upon him with a good eye.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="46" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVI.</hi> Fauſto Poli.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FAuſto Poli,</hi> born in <hi>Caſſia,</hi> a place upon the confines of <hi>Abbuozzo</hi> within the Dioceſſe of <hi>Norcia;</hi> He was a poor man at firſt, and ſerved <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth at ſuch time as he was Biſhop of <hi>Spoletto,</hi> and had the good hap to continue in his ſervice untill his exaltation to the Papacie; and then putting himſelf into the Prelacie, he was after ſome time as a confident ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant of his promoted by <hi>Urban</hi> to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let Gown, together with many other ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of the Apoſtolical Palace. <hi>Poli</hi> hath alwaies been much eſteemed of, and loved by all the <hi>Barberini,</hi> for his ſerviceableneſs to them in the managing of their houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold affaires, for which he is onely good,
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:115287:76"/>being otherwiſe altogether ignorant, and without any known vertue in him. The <hi>Barberini</hi> would not exclude him from the Papacie, in regard he is their creature; but he is not deſired of the <hi>Auſtrians,</hi> and then too there are other perſons of quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, and age in the ſacred Colledge, which farre excel him in all requiſites appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to a Pope; and therefore he may ſet his heart at reſt, and never think of it. This Cardinal is ſo much for the <hi>Barbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rini,</hi> that he will alwaies be at their diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing, and conſequently will ever ſide with the <hi>French.</hi> He is rich, and in caſe he ſhould be Pope, the Biſhop of <hi>Amelia</hi> his Nephew will be he that ſhall reigne; who is not very intelligent, is of litle eſteeme in the ſacred Colledge, and leſſe regarded in the Court.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="47" type="cardinal">
               <pb n="141" facs="tcp:115287:76"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>XLVII.</hi> Lellio Falconieri.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>LEllio Falconieri,</hi> was alſo an aſſidual ſervant to <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth; but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he was too talkative, the <hi>Barberini</hi> did not regard him, neither did the Pope in like manner much care for him He was a poor Prelate, but his father dying, left him a great ſumme of money; wherefore <hi>Urban</hi> thought good to ſend him abroad, that he might ſpend ſome of it, and accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly he diſpatched him away Nuntio into <hi>Flanders,</hi> where the Cardinal <hi>Infante,</hi> being advertiſed that the ſaid <hi>Falconieri</hi> was too much a favorer of the <hi>French,</hi> and conſequently a depreſſor of the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niards,</hi> would not receive him, and ſo ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded him from that imployment. After<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards he was by the ſame <hi>Urban</hi> publiſhed for a good Prelate, eſpecially by cauſing him to execute the place of Secretary of the Congregations of the Biſhops &amp; Regu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lars, and then was promoted by him to the Scarlet Gown, with other ſervants of his holineſſe, for two reaſons; the firſt was, at the inſtance of Cardinal <hi>Sachetti,</hi> and
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:115287:77"/>the ſecond, that imported moſt, was, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe in the Warre of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> the ſaid <hi>Falconieri</hi> and his brethren had lent round ſummes of mony to the Apoſtolick See, for otherwiſe he had never had the Hat. This Cardinal is no great friend to the <hi>Barberini,</hi> and in particular to Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Franceſco,</hi> becauſe when the Pope lay a dying, he opened unto him all the miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demeanors, and tyrannical actions which the ſaid <hi>Franceſco</hi> had perpetrated, for the which he hath ever ſince hated him to the death. He is well enough accommodated with the goods of fortune, but is very much wanting in good parts, for he can hardly read and write his own name. The preſent Pope, <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, ſent him Legate to <hi>Bologna,</hi> where he hath reſided a long time, and at this inſtant the Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtrates of that City are ſuitors unto his holineſſe for the continuing of him in that Charge, alledging that they are excee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dingly well ſatisfied with his Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; and this they do for no other rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, but becauſe he is altogether ignorant, and that therefore they rule all things at their pleaſure, ſo that he is there onely as it were <hi>pro forma,</hi> the whole weight of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fairs reſting upon the ſhoulders of my
<pb n="143" facs="tcp:115287:77"/>Lord <hi>Zeccadoro,</hi> who is ſaid to be his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe kinſman. <hi>Falconieri,</hi> in regard of his age, is capable of the Papacie; but as for wiſdome, and vertue he is moſt inſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent. In diſcourſing his ſpeech is ruſtical, and is no way ſplendid, nor liberal, for it is enough to ſay that he is a <hi>Florentine.</hi> He is much delighted with ſports, plaies, and feaſts, and therefore goes continually to the publique Comedies, which are fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently acted in <hi>Bologna.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="25" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XXV.</hi> Franceſco Adriano Ceva.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>FRanceſco Adriano Ceva,</hi> the Duke of <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voy</hi> his Subject: He was a long time an aſſidual ſervant to <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, and after he was a Prelate, whenſoever his holineſſe made any promotions, he was ſtill kept back from being promoted by <hi>Franceſco Barberino,</hi> ſo that if the Pope had dyed he had been excluded: for the ſaid <hi>Barberino,</hi> in regard there was no good correſpondence between them, laboured alwaies to put him in diffidence with <hi>Ur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ban;</hi> that he might not give him the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:115287:78"/>Gown, which notwithſtanding at length he obtained. This Cardinal is rich in meanes, but poor in vertue and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. He hath many Nephewes, but the moſt beloved is Signior <hi>Carlo Franceſco Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>la,</hi> the Sonne of my Lord <hi>Bayla,</hi> the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtorial Advocate, who lives with this his Uncle, which allows him ſcarce a penny in his purſe, ſuch is his avarice: neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe, in caſe he ſhould attain to the Papa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, this would be the reigning Nephew. <hi>Ceva</hi> is not much affected by the Princes of <hi>Savoy</hi> his Lords, becauſe when there is any benefice, or Abbacie void in his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, or other places of their States, he ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver cares to have it demanded for any of thoſe Princes deſerving ſervants, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies ſeekes to apply it to his own, and his kinſmens benefit; neither is he greatly regarded by the Crown of <hi>France,</hi> although he was Nuntio with that Majeſtie, by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon he is alwaies inclined to the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> devotion, &amp; therfore I cannot ſee how he ſhould ever get to <hi>Peters</hi> Chair, becauſe in every event of the Conclave, they would exclude him for the cauſes aforeſaid: The <hi>Auſtrians</hi> too confide little in him, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving, that even as the Dukes of <hi>Savoy</hi> his Lords uſe to doe, who play the turne-coates
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:115287:78"/>upon every motive according to their intereſt, ſo <hi>Ceva</hi> their ſubject would do the like.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="49" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>XLIX.</hi> Angelo Giorio.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>ANgelo Giorio,</hi> a Native of the City of <hi>Camerino,</hi> of a vile progenie, and a poor Prieſt in <hi>Rome;</hi> where having for ſome time kept a ſchool, he left that, and put himſelf to ſerve the Cardinal <hi>Maffeo Barberino</hi> for a tutor to his Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hewes, <hi>Franceſco, Antonio,</hi> and <hi>Thadeo,</hi> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding them daily to the <hi>Roman</hi> Colledge; and withall imploying himſelf very dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently in divers other affairs of the houſe, he wonne his Maſters goodwill and love. Afterwards, <hi>Maffeo</hi> being elected Pope, <hi>Ciorio</hi> entred into the Prelacie, and in a ſhort time thrived ſo well, that he got to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether a good eſtate; whereupon having a long while continued, performing many good ſervices to <hi>Urban,</hi> it ſeemed conve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient to his holineſſe to do him right, and ſo together with other ſervants of his he promoted him to the Scarlet Gown. He
<pb n="146" facs="tcp:115287:79"/>hath brothers, and Nephewes, which in regard of their ruſtical conditions will not let themſelves be ſeen, nor known in the Court. He delights greatly in hunting, and for that he was much made of by the whole houſe of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> and particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly by the Pope. This Cardinal, becauſe he was exalted from nothing, will alwaies be at the diſpoſing and command of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> and conſequently will of force be for the <hi>French</hi> againſt the <hi>Auſtrians.</hi> He is a man of a luſty age, not very old, is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle reſpected in the ſacred Colledge, and at Court is eſteemed as a raking, covetous Cardinal, that for mony would ſell him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf to do any vile thing. He hath no other good in him, but that he is not ſo igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant, as the reſt of <hi>Urbans</hi> ſervants are, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he hath been continually exerciſed in pedantiſm.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="50" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>L.</hi> Vicenzo Coſtaguti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>VIcenzo Coſtaguti,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Genoua</hi> He was Clerk of the Chamber, and did not hope to come ſo ſoon to the Scar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>let
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:115287:79"/>Gown, becauſe he was too young, and alſo for that the Court abounded with many other aged &amp; deſerving perſons; but well-fare the War of the <hi>Barberini,</hi> which made many riſe, that otherwiſe peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture had never been promoted. For <hi>Urban,</hi> being loth to medle with any of the accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulated treaſure, which he had buried under ground for the benefit of his Nep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hewes, and wanting mony to maintain the Warre, exalted many Officers of the Chamber, and then ſold their places to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Prelates; in which manner <hi>Coſtaguti</hi> was promoted. This Cardinal, before he received the Scarlet Gown, together with his father lent a great ſum of mony to the Chamber, and had for ſecuritie thereof the five millions which were laid up in the Caſtle Saint <hi>Angelo</hi> by <hi>Sixtus quintus.</hi> He is a ſplendid, amiable, ſociable, gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle, affable and courteous Lord; he is much eſteemed of by <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, is charitable, well qualified, and of a goodly preſence: He is of no faction, but keeps himſelf neutral, is learned, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telligent; and may truly be called the Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinal of Gold, in regard he paid treble for the Hat. He is held to be very grateful; and therefore he is loved and reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>renced
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:115287:80"/>of all, as he in like manner honors all.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="51" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>LI.</hi> Paolo Emilio Rondanino.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>PAolo Emilio Rondanino,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, and Nephew to the late Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal <hi>Zachia,</hi> that ſought to advance his pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenſions by the help of the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nals, who being diſtaſted with <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rban</hi> the eighth, for that he ſhewed himſelf, as in effect he was, too much <hi>French,</hi> often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times met together, and made divers Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations to depoſe the ſaid <hi>Urban,</hi> after he had held the Papacie thirteen years: And whilſt his holineſſe by reaſon of his ſickneſſe was gone to the Caſtle of <hi>Gandol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fo</hi> for change of air, the ſaid <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinals ſecretly aſſembled in a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, to make Cardinal <hi>Zachia</hi> Pope in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of the ſaid <hi>Urban,</hi> and depoſe him under the pretext of diſabilitie: But it did not ſucceed, for all was made known to his holineſſe, who returning privily to <hi>Rome,</hi> called a conſiſtory, where all the Cardinals being preſent, <hi>Urban</hi> with an
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:115287:80"/>high voice, ſaid alowd, <hi>Where is the new Pope whom you mean to adore?</hi> which the <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> faction hearing, and perceiving they were diſcovered, remained as it were all dead and confounded. Hereupon it was, that <hi>Urban</hi> made the Bull, which enjoy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned every Cardinal, Archbiſhop, Biſhop, and others whatſoever, that had cure of Souls, to go and reſide at their Churches, upon pain of excommunication, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>privation of their Dignities and Benefices; ſo that the poor Cardinal <hi>Lodoviſio,</hi> who lay grievouſly ſick of the Gout, was for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to get him away to his Church of <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logna,</hi> where not long after he dyed with exceſſive pain; and all thoſe beſides which had a hand in that conſpiracie dy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed diſcontented, and contemned; particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly Cardinal <hi>Zachia. Rondanino</hi> was Clerk of the Chamber, and was promoted together with the other Officers of the Chamber, as the ſaid <hi>Coſtaguti</hi> was; but eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially for that he had at his own charge in the time of the War raiſed a company of Cuiraſiers, beſides divers other ſervi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces. This Cardinal is but of a mean un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, and proud in the higheſt degree, inſomuch as he deignes not to render a ſalute unto any perſon that is not
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:115287:81"/>his equal; a diſcurteſie verily worthy of blame. He is wealthy, loves his plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, and is taken with every <hi>Roman</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="52" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>LII.</hi> Giovanni Steffano Donghi.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIovanni Steffano Donghi,</hi> a Gentleman of <hi>Genoua.</hi> He was Clerk of the Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and was ſent by <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the unhappy ſucceſs of Cardinal <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>da's</hi> Negoti ation, Nuntio Apoſtolical, with the Title of Plenipotentiarie, into <hi>Lom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bardy,</hi> for the concluding of a peace with the Princes of <hi>Italy,</hi> where he cauſed him to ſpend the ſecond Clerkſhip of the Chamber, without any profit at all re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dounding to himſelf thereby. He was pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moted to the Scarlet Gown for the ſame end, as his other fellow Clerks were. This Cardinal is a man learned, and curious; he is well reſpected of the Pope, who made him Legate of <hi>Ferrara,</hi> in which Charge he demeaned himſelf with great commendation. He hath many good parts, is affable, courteous, and alſo charitable. He is very rich, and
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:115287:81"/>ſpends enough, but to purpoſe, and not idlely. He is much devoted to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique King, and makes open profeſſion thereof, having his armes ſet up over the Gate of his Palace. In the paſt Conclave he abandoned the <hi>Barberini,</hi> and followed the faction of <hi>Spain,</hi> which holds him in ſome eſteem, all his whole houſe living under the protection thereof.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="53" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIII.</hi> Carlo Roſcetti.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>CArlo Roſcetti,</hi> a Nobleman of <hi>Ferra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra.</hi> He came a young man to <hi>Rome,</hi> where, putting himſelf into the Prelacie, and being imployed by <hi>Franceſco Barberino</hi> in many buſineſſes, he effected them ſo well to his ſatisfaction, that he took a great liking to him, in ſuch ſort as by his mediation he was ſent Nuntio into <hi>Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many,</hi> and returning from that Charge, he was after ſome years diſpatched alſo as Nuntio into <hi>Ireland,</hi> to ſupply the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Catholiques with mony, and animate them to fight for their Religion againſt the Parliament of <hi>England.</hi> Upon his com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming back from thence, he was promoted
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:115287:82"/>to the Scarlet Gown, at the inſtance of the ſaid <hi>Franceſco,</hi> to the end he might there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by oblige him to be ſtill of his faction in all Conclaves, and other occurrences, as accordingly he hath ſhewed himſelf. He was made Biſhop of <hi>Faenza</hi> in <hi>Romagna,</hi> where he was highly eſteemed, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended for a worthy man, and of a Noble diſpoſition. He is a poor Cardinal, and yet for all that he is not ſlack in giving of almes. He is not much devoted to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> is but young, and of a mean underſtanding. The preſent Pope regards him well, albeit he declared him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf but litle affected to him in his electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. He hath brothers, and many kinſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, which are Counts, and Marqueſſes in <hi>Lombardy.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="54" type="cardinal">
               <head>
                  <hi>LIV.</hi> Giovanni De Lugo.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>GIovanni De Lugo,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh</hi> Gentleman. He was a <hi>Jeſuit,</hi> and a great Divine, of whom <hi>Urban</hi> the eighth made uſe in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers occurrences to his no little ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; wherefore he promoted him to the
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:115287:82"/>Scarlet Gown. This Cardinal was ever an honeſt man, and of an exemplary life; but his being a <hi>Ieſuit,</hi> is that which I cannot abide, for he was Maſter of the Schooles of the Colledge, <hi>&amp; hoc ſufficiat.</hi> Some ſay that he was aſſiſted and ſupplyed by his Company; others ſay no, becauſe he hath ſhewed himſelf as it were an enemy to the <hi>Ieſuits;</hi> but that he was aſſiſted by his kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and had alſo got together ſome ſtore of mony to ſuch a uſe, as the manner of the <hi>Ieſuits</hi> is to do, <hi>cum cantionibus, &amp; aliis adminiculis.</hi> His deſcent was not ignoble, and he hath had many men renowned for learning in his houſe. This <hi>Lugo,</hi> by reaſon of the obligation wherein he ſtood farre ingaged to the <hi>Barberini,</hi> made ſhew in the Conclave of following their faction; but afterwards with a ſtratagem he gave his vote to the <hi>Spaniards,</hi> and when as the Pope was elected, publiquely declared himſelf of the <hi>Auſtrian</hi> party: ſo that in him is verified the ſaying; As ingratefull as a <hi>Ieſuit.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="154" facs="tcp:115287:83"/>
               <head>The promotions which were made by <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, and <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth.</head>
               <div n="55" type="cardinal">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LV.</hi> Alfonſo della Queva.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>ALfonſo della Queva,</hi> Marqueſſe of <hi>Medmar,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard;</hi> He was ſent by the Catholique King, Ledger Ambaſſador to the Republique of <hi>Venice;</hi> in the time of whoſe reſidence there, the Duke of <hi>Oſſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na,</hi> Vice-Roy of <hi>Naples,</hi> ſent a very migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Fleet to take that City by ſurpriſe; for holding intelligence with ſome traitors in it. He had made an agreement with them, that they ſhould ſet the famous Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenal thereof on fire, to the end that whilſt every one was running thither for to help to quench it, the Fleet might enter at their pleaſure, and ſeize on the moſt important places of the City; but the plot being diſcovered before it came to execution, and the Nobilitie believing that the Marqueſſe of <hi>Queva</hi> was privie and conſenting to that treaſon; went to
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:115287:83"/>the Palace where he dwelt, to cut him and all his Family in pieces; but being forewarned thereof, he fled with all ſpeed in a Gondola towards <hi>Rome,</hi> where a few monthes after he was by <hi>Gregory</hi> the fifteenth with the aſſent of the Catholique King promoted to the Scarlet Gown; and after ſome yeares he was by his Majeſtie made Governor of <hi>Flanders</hi> and the Low-Countries, where he carried himſelf with the little ſatisfaction of thoſe people, by ſeeking the ruine of that Country for the inriching of himſelf; but the Catholique King being advertiſed of his ill Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, deprived him of that Charge, and diſgraced him in ſuch manner, as he was alſo bereft of all the revenues and profits which he enjoyed in the Kingdomes of <hi>Spain;</hi> by reaſon wherof he was ſo exhauſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that he ran mightily in debt. After the aſſumption of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the death of Cardinal <hi>Creſcentio,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by the Biſhoprick of <hi>Paleſtina</hi> became void, which by way of ſenioritie apper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained unto the ſaid Cardinal <hi>della Queva,</hi> who therefore was deſired by Cardianl <hi>Carlo de Medici</hi> to reſign it unto him, to the end that remaining in that City, which bore the Title of <hi>Don Tadeos</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalitie,
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:115287:84"/>he might croſſe and vex the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berini;</hi> and this he promiſed <hi>Don Carlo</hi> to doe, but never performed it; for the <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berini</hi> prevented this diſorder by giving <hi>Queva</hi> I know not how many thouſands of crownes not to reſigne the Biſhoprick, ſo that he was not ſo good as his word to the ſaid Prince Cardinal, for which he was very much blamed of every one. He is a very learned man, and a great wit. He is ſomewhat eſteemed in the Colledge, but little reſpected in the Court, having no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther train but his own Caroches, as one that is not capable of the Papacie, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he is a <hi>Spaniard:</hi> and the very <hi>Spani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ards</hi> themſelves too make no great recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of him, holding him as inconfident, although he ſtrives with all ardor to ſhew himſelf more affectionate and diligent in the Kings ſervice and affairs, then any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther perſon whatſoever. He is of a good and exemplary life, and for his know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge and doctrine is beloved of his holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="56" type="cardinal">
                  <pb n="157" facs="tcp:115287:84"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVI.</hi> Marcello Lanti.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>MArcello Lanti,</hi> a <hi>Roman</hi> Nobleman, Deane of the ſacred Colledge, and Nephew to <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, being the Son of a Siſter of his. He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown by the ſaid <hi>Paul,</hi> is a very old man, of an holy converſation, of a moſt innocent life, and marvellous chari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table. He is of kinne to the greateſt part of the <hi>Roman</hi> Nobilitie, and alſo to the Great Duke of <hi>Toſcan.</hi> He hath enjoyed the Scarlet Gown forty years, and yet is for all that ignorant, teſty, &amp; obſtinate. He was not nominated in the laſt Conclave, for that the <hi>Barberini</hi> durſt not conſide in him, by reaſon of his affinitie with the <hi>Borgheſi,</hi> and Great Duke, as aforeſaid. he is head of the Congregation of the Biſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ops, and Regulars, and if he live to a va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant Sea, he may chance get into <hi>Peters</hi> Chair. He makes open profeſſion of his devotion to the houſe of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> although the Marqueſſe his brother, lately dead, was alwaies <hi>French.</hi> This Cardinal would not be amiſſe for the good, and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
<pb n="158" facs="tcp:115287:85"/>of the Church, for he is a peaceable man, is excedingly well eſteemed of by the Sacred Colledge, and <hi>Roman</hi> Court, is alſo greatly reſpected by the Princes, and hath not any Cardinal his Enemy; wherefore he may very well attain to the Papacie, as is much deſired of all he ſhould; but whilſt the <hi>Barberini</hi> live, he will hardly come to be Pope, for they have been ſufficiently puniſhed by the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth <hi>Pamphilio.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="57" type="cardinal">
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVII.</hi> Carlo de Medeci.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>CArlo de Medeci,</hi> a <hi>Florentine,</hi> Uncle to the Great Duke of <hi>Toſcan,</hi> and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to the late Queen Mother of <hi>France.</hi> He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown as a great Prince, and therefore he is in high eſteem, and Authoritie with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Colledge, and all the Court. He was the principal Author of the election of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenth, who out of his Obliga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Gratitude beares a great affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to this Prince. He was, and is an Enemy
<pb n="159" facs="tcp:115287:85"/>to all the houſe of the <hi>Barberini</hi> for divers occaſions, but the chiefeſt was their War with the Great Duke. He is a Lord of a clear underſtanding, beloved of every one, courteous, ſplendid, and delighting in pleaſures, and recreations. He is migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tily affected to the Family of <hi>Auſtria,</hi> ſo that he could be contented, as one may ſay, to have even his ſkinne plucked over his eares for the King of <hi>Spain.</hi> He is of a great age, but appeares not to be ſo, by reaſon of the corpulencie of his body. No more is, or ought to be ſaid of this Cardi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal, being a great Prince, and as ſuch a one, I leave him.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="58" type="cardinal">
                  <pb n="160" facs="tcp:115287:86"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LVIII.</hi> Baldaſſare di Sandoval.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BAldaſſare di Sandoval,</hi> a <hi>Spaniard,</hi> and Biſhop of <hi>Sivil.</hi> He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown at the inſtance of the Catholique King, by whom he was after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards ſent Ambaſſador to <hi>Rome,</hi> in which Charge he carried him ſelf with the ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction and commendation of both the parties. Upon the end of that imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment he returned into <hi>Spain,</hi> where being kept from receiving audience of the King by the Count-Duke, he one day baſtinado<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him with the ſame battoon, wherewith he ſuſtained himſelf being lame of the goute; in revenge whereof the Count-Duke, cauſed the horſes of his Caroach to be cudgeld whilſt he was in it. <hi>Sandoval</hi> was he, that in his firſt Audience diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the miſdemeanors of the ſaid Count-Duke, and alſo the loſſe of the Kingdom of <hi>Portugal,</hi> of <hi>Catalogna,</hi> and other States; whereof the King perceiving the truth, turned him out of his favor, and redu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced him to thoſe termes, that he was fain to live exiled from the Court in a Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try
<pb n="161" facs="tcp:115287:86"/>houſe of his. This Cardinal is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry highly eſteemed, and exceedingly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loved of the King, is very old, of a good converſation, bountiful, of great authori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and well liked of every one. He is a great friend of <hi>Innocent</hi> the tenths, having held a ſtrickt correſpondence with him at ſuch time as he was Nuntioia <hi>Naples,</hi> and in <hi>Spain,</hi> which he continued with him whilſt he was at <hi>Rome.</hi> He was not preſent in the laſt Conclave, by reaſon of the lenggth of the voyage, and his great age, which is ſuch, as he can ſtand no man in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſtead hereafter, becauſe he will never be able to come into the Conclave again.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="59" type="cardinal">
                  <pb n="162" facs="tcp:115287:87"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LIX.</hi> Agoſtino Spinola.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>AGoſtino Spinola,</hi> a <hi>Genoueſe</hi> of the old Nobilitie, and brother to the late Marqueſſe <hi>Spinola,</hi> that moſt famous Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain. He was promoted to the Scarlet Gown by <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, at the inſtance of the Catholique King. He was Archbiſhop of <hi>Compoſtella,</hi> from which he is removed, and hath the Archbiſhoprick of <hi>Toledo</hi> in lieu thereof conferred on him, with a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of ten thouſand Crownes a year. He is exceedingly beloved of his Catholique Majeſtie, for his brothers merits; is of kinne to the greateſt part of the <hi>Genoueſe</hi> Nobilitie, is very rich, and ſo old, that in regard of the length of the way he could not come to the laſt Conclave, nor can he be at the next, unleſſe he ſets forth two monthes before the death of the Pope. He is a Lord of a good diſpoſition, ſplendid, and charitable. His vote, according to his obligation to the Catholique King, will alwaies be for the <hi>Spaniſh</hi> faction. When he was young, he delighted in taking all the pleaſure that poſſibly he could, never ſtanding upon mony.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="60" type="cardinal">
                  <pb n="163" facs="tcp:115287:87"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>LX.</hi> Giulio Cardinal Roma.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GIulio Cardinal Roma,</hi> of a Noble Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the ſtate of <hi>Milan,</hi> who having put himſelf into the Prelacie, was promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to the Scarlet Gown by <hi>Paul</hi> the fifth, becauſe he knew him to be both learned, and deſerving. The City of <hi>Rome</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard of his excellent qualities expects great things from him; for being a good and conſciencious man, it is believed that he will be Pope if he live; but ſhould that come to paſſe, I doubt he would be too rigorous, eſpecially when Eccleſiaſtical matters are concerned: for he could be contented to put not onely his houſe, but his own life in jeopardie, for the Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance of the Churches decorum; being naturally ſtiffe and obſtinate in favor of the Eccleſiaſtical jurisdiction. <hi>Franceſco Barberino</hi> would willingly have ſtickled in the laſt Conclave for his advancement to the Papacie, but that he could not truſt him, becauſe he was a <hi>Milaneſe;</hi> fearing, leaſt as one of that Country, he ſhould deal with him, and all the houſe of the
<pb n="162" facs="tcp:115287:88"/>
                     <hi>Barberini,</hi> as <hi>Pius quartus,</hi> who was likewiſe a <hi>Milaneſe,</hi> did with the <hi>Caraffeſchi;</hi> and bring him to make reſtitution of the mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny taken out of Caſtle <hi>Angelo;</hi> as alſo ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der a ſtrict accompt of his adminiſtration. This Cardinal is head of the Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which are held in his own houſe. He is a very knowing Lord, of a good diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, and of an exemplary life. In nego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating he ſhewes himſelf very affectio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate, is much reſpected of the ſacred Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, and is greatly eſteemed in the Court. He is beloved of the Catholique King, and is exceedingly deſired by the Great Duke, and the Republique of <hi>Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nice,</hi> but little enough by the Crown of <hi>France.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:115287:88"/>
            <head>A Table of the Cardinals.</head>
            <list>
               <item>
                  <hi>1.</hi> GIovanni Carlo de Medici. <hi>pag. 1</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>2.</hi> Domenico Cecchini. <hi>pag. 2</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>3.</hi> Nicolo Albergati. <hi>pag. 4</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>4.</hi> Horatio Giuſtiniano. <hi>pag. 7</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>5.</hi> Alderano Cibo. <hi>pag. 9</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>6.</hi> Pier Luigi Caraffa. <hi>pag. 11</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>7.</hi> Federico Sforza. <hi>pag. 15</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>8.</hi> Tiberio Cenci. <hi>pag. 17</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>9.</hi> Benedetto Odeſcalcho, <hi>pag. 21</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>10.</hi> Fabritio Savelli. <hi>pag. 23</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>11.</hi> Franceſco Cherubino. <hi>pag. 27</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>12.</hi> Chriſtofforo Vidman. <hi>pag. 28</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>13.</hi> Lorenzo Roggi. <hi>pag. 30</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>14.</hi> Franceſco Maidalchini. <hi>pag. 36</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>15.</hi> Franceſco Barberino. <hi>pag. 41</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>16.</hi> Erneſto Adalberto d'Arach. <hi>pag. 50</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>17.</hi> Giulio Sachetti. <hi>pag. 51</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>18.</hi> Bernardino Spada. <hi>pag. 55</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>19.</hi> Fe derico Cornaro. <hi>pag. 63</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>20.</hi> Martio Ginetti. <hi>pag. 65</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:115287:89"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>21.</hi> Antonio Barberino. <hi>pag. 86</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>22.</hi> Girolamo Colonna. <hi>pag. 72</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>23.</hi> Cirriaco Rocci. <hi>pag. 76</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>24.</hi> Giovanni Battiſta Palotta. <hi>pag. 78</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>25.</hi> Theodoro Trivultio. <hi>pag. 83</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>26.</hi> Steffano Durazzo. <hi>pag. 89</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>27.</hi> Marc' Antonio Franciotti. <hi>pag. 87</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>28.</hi> Federico Carpegna. <hi>pag. 90</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>29.</hi> Franceſco Maria Brancaccio. <hi>pag. 91</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>30.</hi> Rinaldo d'Eſte. <hi>pag. 95</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>31.</hi> Franceſco Peretti, <hi>alias</hi> Cardinal Montalto, <hi>pag. 99</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>32.</hi> Giulio Mazzarini. <hi>pag. 102</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>33.</hi> Marc' Antonio Bragadini. <hi>pag. 106</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>34.</hi> Pietro Donato Ceſis. <hi>pag. 108</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>35.</hi> Franceſco Maria Machiavelli. <hi>pag. 110</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>36.</hi> Verginio Orſini. <hi>pag. 112</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>37.</hi> Giulio Gabrielli. <hi>pag. 115</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>38.</hi> Aſcanio Filomarini, <hi>pag. 117</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>39.</hi> Gieronimo Verospi, <hi>pag. 124</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>40.</hi> Gaspare Matthei. <hi>pag. 126</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>41,</hi> Girolamo Grimaldi. <hi>pag. 127</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>42.</hi> Ceſare Fachinetti. <hi>pag. 131</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>43.</hi> Franceſco Rapaccioli, <hi>pag. 132</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>44.</hi> Giovanni Giacomo Panzirolo. <hi>pag. 134</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>45.</hi> Mattheo Theodoli. <hi>pag. 136</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>46.</hi> Fauſto Poli. <hi>pag. 139</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>47.</hi> Lellio Falconieri. <hi>pag. 141</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>48</hi> Franceſco Adriano Ceva. <hi>pag. 143</hi>
               </item>
               <pb facs="tcp:115287:89"/>
               <item>
                  <hi>49.</hi> Angelo Giorio. <hi>pag. 146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>50</hi> Vicenzo Coſtaguti. <hi>pag. 146</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>51.</hi> Paolo Emilio Rondanino, <hi>pag. 148</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>52.</hi> Giovanni Steffano Donghi. <hi>pag. 150</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>53.</hi> Carlo Roſcetti. <hi>pag. 151</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>54.</hi> Giovanni de lugo. <hi>pag. 152</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>55.</hi> Alfonſo della Queva. <hi>pag. 154</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>56.</hi> Marcello Lanti. <hi>pag. 157</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>57.</hi> Carlo de Medici. <hi>pag. 158</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>58.</hi> Baldaſſare di Sandova. <hi>pag. 160</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>59.</hi> Agoſtino Spinola. <hi>pag. 162</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <hi>60.</hi> Giulio Cardinal Roma. <hi>pag. 163</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
